<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of the Right Reverend Father in God, Edw. Rainbow, D.D. late Lord Bishop of Carlisle to which is added, a sermon preached at his funeral by Thomas Tully, his lordship's chaplain, and chancellor of the said diocess of Carlisle; at Dalston, April the 1st. 1684.</title>
            <author>Banks, Jonathan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11914840</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11914840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 807:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of the Right Reverend Father in God, Edw. Rainbow, D.D. late Lord Bishop of Carlisle to which is added, a sermon preached at his funeral by Thomas Tully, his lordship's chaplain, and chancellor of the said diocess of Carlisle; at Dalston, April the 1st. 1684.</title>
                  <author>Banks, Jonathan.</author>
                  <author>Tully, T. (Thomas), 1620-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[19], 122, 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Roycroft, for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rainbowe, Edward, 1608-1684.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:1"/>
            <p> Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aug. 29. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Rob. Midgley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Dr. Edward Rainbow</figDesc>
                  <q>THE EFFIGIES OF THE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ATHER IN GOD DR. EDWARD RAINBOW LATE BISHOP <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>F CARLISLE AETAT.74</q>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>His face you see; but not his noble mind:</l>
                        <l>That like his fame, was great and unconfin'd;</l>
                        <l>Yet humble too, and honors would prevent:</l>
                        <l>But's virtues built the greateſt momum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt.</l>
                        <l>Which all devouring time cannot deface,</l>
                        <l>Till the world wants both gratitude and grace.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:2"/>
            <p> THE LIFE Of the Right Reverend Father in God,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDW. RAINBOW,</hi> D. D. Late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, A SERMON Preached at his Funeral by <hi>Thomas Tully,</hi> his Lordſhips Chaplain, and Chancellor of the ſaid Dioceſs of <hi>Carliſle;</hi> At <hi>Dalſton, April</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> 1684.</p>
            <bibl>PROV. X. 7.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The memory of the Juſt is bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <bibl>HEB. XI. 4.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>By it he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> at the Weſt-End of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1688.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>TO write the Lives of Great and Good Men, hath been the peculiar Care of Perſons of all Ages and Religions; and this as well to tranſmit their Names and Actions to Poſterity, and to make them (as it were) live after death, as to propagate their Opinions, and to excite others to the proſecution of thoſe Vertues, which have
<pb facs="tcp:50921:4"/> contributed to make their Names immortal. Hence among the Heathens, nothing was more carefully attended to, than the Writing of their Hiſtories; In which parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and the <hi>Perſians</hi> excelled. For they generally would not ſuffer any to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pile the Hiſtories of their own Countries, but ſuch as were appointed thereto on purpoſe. And among thoſe, as the <hi>Babylonians</hi> had their Public Archives; ſo had the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> their Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, on which in Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick Notes and Sacred
<pb facs="tcp:50921:4"/> Characters they were wont to Record their memorable Acts. Nor were the <hi>Romans</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to thoſe Polite Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in this Point; ſince they had their <hi>Pontifices Maximi,</hi> to make up their Public Records or Annals. But above all others, the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> ſo renowned for their Government and happy Inventions, do herein merit alſo the largeſt Fame, having generally in their Hiſtorians, as well as Princes, but the ſame continued Series.</p>
            <p>To come nigher to the preſent Subject; What hath been more Read, and that
<pb facs="tcp:50921:5"/> with Applauſe, among the <hi>Latin</hi> Hiſtorians, than <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi>'s Lives, and <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi>'s Morals among the <hi>Greeks.</hi> Not to mention, That <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great had a <hi>Curtius,</hi> and an <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who undertook, that the Memory of his Victories, wherewith that young Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror overran <hi>Aſia,</hi> and made <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Afric</hi> to tremble, ſhould not periſh in the ſame Grave with him.</p>
            <p>To paſs on to the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers; <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> wrote their Lives, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well or ill I ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:50921:5"/> now determine; but add, that even <hi>Apollonius Tya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> one of the worſt of Men, wanted not his <hi>Damis</hi> and <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> to conſign the Memoirs of that Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical <hi>Pythagorean</hi> to after Ages.</p>
            <p>And not to dwell any longer among the Heathens, The <hi>Jews,</hi> who were taught by immediate Revelation from Heaven, had their Prieſts to Regiſter the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Republic. Nor were the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as they profeſt the beſt Religion, leſs careful than others, to have the gallant Actions of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:50921:6"/> Primitive Hero's tranſcribed and committed to Poſterity. And therefore Care was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, That there ſhould be Notaries in every Church, (and that early too) which were to tranſcribe the Acts of the Martyrs, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their Diſcourſes, and the circumſtances of their Sufferings, that in thoſe Days of Trial, others might be encouraged to aſpire to that Celeſtial Glory, which was to be the Sequel of ſo many famous Terreſtrial Miſeries.</p>
            <p>And in the Fourth Age, when Chriſtianity begun to
<pb facs="tcp:50921:6"/> triumph over Paganiſm, as having Chriſtian Emperors for its Nurſing Fathers, thô ſore afflicted by the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Hereſie of <hi>Arius,</hi> as it was the moſt Learned Age, that (at leaſt) the Primitive Church had; ſo nothing was more common than a recital of their Vertues at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of good Men, and thoſe deſcribed with all the Eloquence and Ornament, that Truth, aſſiſted with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Learning, could bear. Which ſtrains of Rhetoric, however abus'd by the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Ignorance of the following Ages, were only
<pb facs="tcp:50921:7"/> deſign'd, that the Living ſhould Copy after thoſe fair Patterns, which thoſe dying Worthies had ſet them.</p>
            <p>To omit others, we have Saint <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> juſtly ſtyled the Divine, not ſcrupling in his Funeral Orations to commend his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Gregory,</hi> his Brother <hi>Caeſarius,</hi> and his Siſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> notwithſtanding the nearneſs of their Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that flowing Vein of Oratory, which he had ſo often ſeen opened at <hi>Athens.</hi> He there opened all the Boxes of his Perfuming Eloquence, that the ſweet
<pb facs="tcp:50921:7"/> Odor of their Vertues might be diffuſed with a more chearing fragrancy.</p>
            <p>This was the Practice of that Age, which celebrated Vertue in Perſons, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed thereby from the Crowd of common and bare Profeſſors, by Men, thô not much ſeparated in Blood. And it was by ſuch Inſtances, that <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſhewed what it could do, when its Divine Precepts are ſtrictly obſerved, and what Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Praiſe and Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude it hath erected to its Glorious Founder in every Age.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:8"/>
            <p> And althô this Reverend Biſhop, whoſe <hi>Life</hi> is now deſign'd to be written, was a great Example of true Piety in his Generation; yet hath he not been ſo happy as to meet with a Pen ſit to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his Actions to ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Times; thô, to balance that Defect, what hath been done in the following Sheets is with all fidelity and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. As he deteſted Flattery when living, ſo (I hope) there hath nothing been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered here, which will not endure the ſhock of <hi>Envy</hi> as to the Verity in matters of Fact; and thoſe expreſſed
<pb facs="tcp:50921:8"/> in a plain Style, like the <hi>Life</hi> of the Original. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe true Merit, like true and native Beauty, needs no <hi>Fucus,</hi> no Adulterate Paint to ſet it off to advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50921:9"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50921:9"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF Dr. <hi>Edward Rainbow,</hi> LATE Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DOctor <hi>Edward Rainbow</hi> was Born at <hi>Bliton,</hi> a Village in <hi>Lindſey Coaſt</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> near unto <hi>Gainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> a noted Market Town
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50921:10"/> upon <hi>Trent,</hi> that Engliſh <hi>Ganges,</hi> which divides this Kingdom into two parts, Southern and Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern.</p>
            <p>The Day in which he firſt drew breath was the Twentieth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the Year of Grace One thouſand Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Eight; a Year not forgotten in our <hi>Engliſh Annals,</hi> ſince in it there were three <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Biſhops Conſecrated by Men of the ſame Sacred Order in this Nation, our Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby made at leaſt a Nurſe to that of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And no leſs remarkable was it for extending the Civil power of our Monarchs, together with the propagation of the Goſpel, by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> planting of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> althô formerly diſcovered by the learned and unfortunate Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50921:10"/>
            <p> As an honeſt Extraction is that which gives a greater luſtre to all perſons, and often recommends them more eaſily to the eſteem of others; ſo cannot this our Right Reverend and Worthy Prelate be without Injuſtice deny'd that reſpect which is due to one vertuouſly deſcended, He deriving his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal from Parents more good than great, and eminent for their Piety and real Worth.</p>
            <p>His Father, Mr. <hi>Thomas Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow</hi> was a Reverend Divine, noted for his Learning and Vertue, who after his being educated at <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> was firſt preſented to the Rectory of <hi>Bliton</hi> above-mentioned, and then to that of <hi>Wintringham<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in the ſame County of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> ſituate upon <hi>Humber,</hi> that great <hi>Aeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arium,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50921:11"/> where ſo many Rivers meet e're they pay their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to the Ocean: Both which Places were conferr'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by the Worſhipful Family of the <hi>Wrays</hi> of <hi>Glent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he is ſaid to have well deſerved ſuch Advancement, being a Man, who preached as well to his Pariſhioners by his exemplary good Life, as by his ſound Doctrin; and when he dy'd (thô I cannot learn certainly when that was) left the Odor of a good Name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him.</p>
            <p>Nor was his Mother, Mrs. <hi>Rebecca Allen,</hi> Daughter to Mr. <hi>David Allen,</hi> Rector of <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> in <hi>Lindſey-Coaſt</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeid, an unfit Conſort for ſo Worthy a Man. For, to many of thoſe good qualifications of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50921:11"/> a Woman mentioned by the wiſeſt of Kings, ſhe added that of the knowledge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures even in the Original Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, being trained up by her Father to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Latin,</hi> the <hi>Greek,</hi> and the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> So that, if the Female Sex, <hi>Euſtochium</hi> and others have been ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by S. <hi>Hierom</hi> for their great Skill in the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, the Praiſe that this excellent Matron merited in this kind ought not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Which is alſo a preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant inſtance, that the other Sex is not incapable of ſome of the moſt profound Studies, and not altogether unfit to walk in the moſt retired Paths of Learning.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Edward Rainbow</hi> had the Name of <hi>Edward</hi> given
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50921:12"/> him from his Godfather Mr. <hi>Edward Wray</hi> of <hi>Rycot,</hi> who was younger Brother to Sir <hi>John Wray</hi> the elder, and who was a great Courtier and Favourite of the elder <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> by whoſe Intereſt Mr <hi>Wray</hi> married the Heireſs of the Honour and Fortune of the Lord <hi>Norris</hi> of <hi>Rycot,</hi> and to whom joyntly with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sir <hi>John Wray,</hi> his God-Son Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> afterwards dedicated his firſt printed Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Preached at S. <hi>Pauls Croſs,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Labour forbidden and commanded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return whence we have digreſſed a little; From ſuch pious Parents, who can doubt but <hi>Edward Rainbow</hi> met with a good Education? Goodneſs, is diffuſive of it ſelf by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and moſt eſpecially
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50921:12"/> when ſeated in thoſe of ſo near a Relation as Parents to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. The ſenſe of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the firſt quickens their deſires of propagating their Vertues in their Off-ſpring, as well as continuing in them their Names to Poſterity. And accordingly this vertuous Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple took great care early to inſtil into this their Son the Principles of Religion, a great and cordial Love for his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Lord and Maſter, and a juſt Fear to offend him in the breach of any of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Commands. They taught him to aſpire to the poſſeſſion of that Celeſtial Country, where that love for true Piety would be as unbounded as that God who is the Original of it. And doubtleſs the early cultivating of ſo hopeful a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50921:13"/> Plant was not ineffectual as the Sequel ſhew'd. He had been taught that this Life was but a Pilgrimage, and what would be the concluſion of minding his walking therein ſoon, which made him haſten his pace to Heaven-ward: For Travellers never haſten ſo much, as when they expect good Lodgings at their Journeys end.</p>
            <p>His Infancy being paſt, about Nine years of Age he was ſent to <hi>Fillingham,</hi> a Village in the ſo often mentioned County of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> where his Grandmother <hi>Allen,</hi> and his Ant <hi>Peachel</hi> his Mothers Siſter, lived. At which place he begun to lay the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Secular Learning; which his Parents, obſerving him to be very capable of improving to a conſiderable height, ſent him in <hi>A. Dom.</hi> 1619. to the publick
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50921:13"/> School of <hi>Gainsborough,</hi> and from thence in <hi>April</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. to <hi>Peterborow</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> to be one of the Scholars of Dr. <hi>John Williams,</hi> who was then Prebend of that Church. And it was upon his account that <hi>Edward Rainbow</hi> was ſent to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> School in <hi>June</hi> 1621; Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> old Mr. <hi>Rainbows</hi> great Friend, being advanced to the Deanry of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and the Biſhoprick of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and conſequently had thereby better opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to gratifie his Friends Son in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where he then choſe to reſide.</p>
            <p>In all theſe ſhort Stages of his Youth, he was ſo far from fruſtrating the Hopes which his Parents had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of him, that the great Proficiency under his ſeveral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50921:14"/> Maſters, adorned with his meek and obliging humor, eaſily gained him the Favour of his Inſtructors, and the Eſteem of his more diligent School-Fellows. In which ſtate he continued till fitted for the Univerſity; and then he was ſent to <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> College in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in <hi>July</hi> 1623. at the Age of Fifteen; where his elder Brother <hi>John</hi> was admitted, and died Fellow of that Houſe.</p>
            <p>He had before this, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>March</hi> 1621, loſt his dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which loſs gave him all the diſturbance that a dutiful Son was capable of, for the Death of ſo prudent and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Mother, and whom he never mentioned without Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Nor did ſhe dye lamented by him alone; but by all thoſe who were acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50921:14"/> with her extraordinary Parts and religious Converſation, and who were not generally Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of, or Strangers to true Vertue.</p>
            <p>Having paid the Debt due to the memory of his good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I am obliged to reſume the Thred of his Hiſtory, and conſequently to mention, that during his ſtay in <hi>Oxford</hi> he applied himſelf to his Studies with that attention, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Son of ſo Learned a Father; which courſe he held on in <hi>Magdalen</hi> College in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> whither he was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in <hi>June</hi> 1. 1625, and that upon the following occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Right Honourable and truly Noble Lady, <hi>Frances,</hi> Counteſs Dowager of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and Daughter to Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Wray,</hi> ſometimes Lord Chief
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50921:15"/> Juſtice of <hi>England;</hi> as ſhe inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited her Fathers Liberality, who had been a great Benefactor to the laſt mentioned College of <hi>Magdalen,</hi> in giving Lands and Moneys to it for the Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Fellowſhip and two Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larſhips; ſo did ſhe alſo inherit the kindneſs of her Family to that of <hi>Edward Rainbow,</hi> and therefore in her life time did him that honour to nominate him one of her Scholars there: Upon which account (as hath been already hinted) he remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Oxon</hi> thither, and was admitted into that College and Scholarſhip at the time above-mentioned.</p>
            <p>He took his Degree of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelor of Arts there in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1627, and commenced Maſter of Arts in 1630; a Year which is ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50921:15"/> in Hiſtory for the Birth of our late Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second; and for the deſcent of <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> into <hi>Germany;</hi> where, till death put a Period to his Martial Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Victory ſeem'd to be his conſtant Attendant.</p>
            <p>In <hi>July</hi> after he had proceeded Maſter of Arts, he was ſent for to teach the Free-School at <hi>Kirton</hi> in <hi>Lindſey Coaſt</hi> (three or four Miles from <hi>Bliton)</hi> which was profered to him, by that Great Patron of his Family, Sir <hi>John Wray,</hi> whither he went; chuſing rather to be employed, thô in a low Station, where he might be ſerviceable to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, than to indulge himſelf in eaſe and idleneſs, which are not ſeldom the incentives to Vice, and too often do prove the ruine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50921:16"/> of the moſt hopeful young Men.</p>
            <p>But before we conduct him from <hi>Barnwell</hi> in <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> from Mr. <hi>Botelers,</hi> who had married his Mothers Siſter, whither he had ſometimes before retired by reaſon of the hot Sickneſs, give me leave to add, that as few Graduates, at leaſt ſuch as are Maſters of Arts, and have behaved themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statutes of the Univerſity, do depart thence without a Teſtimony under the public Seal of that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; ſo he had, together with that, an unuſual Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation from that Learned Body.</p>
            <p>For, during his ſtay there, he had early given ſuch undeniable proofs of his being the Maſter of a prompt and facetious Wit, and that upon ſeveral accidental
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50921:16"/> and leſs remarkable occaſions, that he was thereby ſufficiently diſtinguiſhed from the Crowd and the Fame hereof, put him and it to ſo unuſual a trial, that perhaps the Hiſtory of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Univerſity cannot furniſh us with many Parallels thereto.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tripos,</hi> who was at the Scholars Act choſen to divert rhe Univerſity with his Wit, did it with ſo much Sarcaſm and Abuſe, and with ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Reflections upon the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Perſons in that Eminent Body, that the Vice-Chancellor not ſuffering him any longer to continue in his Scurrility, had ordered him to be pull'd Our Mr. <hi>Rainbow,</hi> thô unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and without the leaſt fore thought, was called up to ſucceed him in that ſlippery place of Honour. Which diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50921:17"/> Province, (and made then more difficult by the public Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand of his Predeceſſor) he managed ſo dexterouſly, and made his extemporary Speech with ſo facetious an Air, and delivered it ſo ſmoothly and agreeably, that far from daſhing againſt the Rock of <hi>Cenſure,</hi> which the other had ſplit upon, he procured the general ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his Auditors, and a juſt Applauſe to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Nor had he before this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture gained himſelf leſs E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem in that College of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> where he had been Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, than in that more public Stage of the Univerſity. For, among others, Dr. <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> who was then Maſter of that College, being the Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> ſometimes Lord
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50921:17"/> Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by him to that place, and one who was an able Judge of a Scholars worth, having taken notice of Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi>'s excellent Parts and good deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was very deſirous to have retained him in the College. But there being then no proſpect of any Preferment that might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him to ſtay, the Worthy Doctor conſented, thô not without ſome reluctancy, to Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi>'s removal to <hi>Kirton</hi> School aforeſaid. Which labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious employment, ſo uneaſie to moſt ingenuous Perſons, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged a little while with more ſatisfaction to thoſe Men, whoſe Children were entruſted to his Care, than to himſelf. For this new Charge being not ſo agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his inclinations, he quitted it e're long and went to <hi>London</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50921:18"/> with two or three more of the ſame ſtanding and College; after he had by the way paid a viſit to his Friends in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and ſetled himſelf at <hi>Fullers Rents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he went into Sacred Orders, I cannot learn; for he hath in his Diaries very rarely taken any notice of any Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beſtowed on him, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with that low and mean Opinion he entertained of himſelf; only this I find, that the firſt time he Preached was in <hi>April</hi> 1632, at <hi>Glentworth;</hi> by which may be collected, that he was not admitted into Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders till he had commenced Maſter of Arts.</p>
            <p>He ſtayed a Quarter of a year in <hi>Fullers Rents,</hi> whence he removed to <hi>Sion College,</hi> for the benefit of the good Library in that place. And he enjoy'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50921:18"/> himſelf and his Friends freely and without noiſe; and as he thirſted after more Knowledge, and daily improved it in that Retirement, ſo he had in the year following ſome hopes of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the benefit of others (thô he was ſufficiently averſe to all oſtentation) in becoming Chaplain to that Worthy and Learned Society of <hi>Lincolns Inn.</hi> And there he met with no ſmall encouragment in his Pretenſions, having gain'd the approbation of the moſt Judicious Perſons concerned in that Election; but he ſucceeded not in his deſign, another man (who had a lowder Voice) being preferr'd before him.</p>
            <p>And now, leſt his diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould tempt him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond, the All-wiſe God, who knew beſt what was fit for him, and who never fails thoſe that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50921:19"/> diligently ſeek and ſerve him, as we may charitably conclude our Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> then did, ſince he hath left ſo many Teſtimonies of his private Devotion in his <hi>Diaries;</hi> He, I ſay, did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him in his exigency. For, after this generous diſmiſſion, rather than refuſal of him at <hi>Lincolns Inn,</hi> where he had ſtayed two or three Months, he was in <hi>June</hi> the ſame year made Curate at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and from thence invited to return to his beloved College of <hi>Magdalen,</hi> by Doctor <hi>Smith,</hi> the Maſter, and ſome of the Fellows, with the profer of the firſt Fellowſhip that fell. Any Preferment in that place was like to be acceptable to Mr. <hi>Rainbow;</hi> but the thought thereof had an irreſiſtible Charm to bring him thither, when ſeconded with the kindneſs of that Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50921:19"/> which (in contradiction to the old Proverb) forgot him not in his Abſence.</p>
            <p>The Profer was noble and tempting and met with an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſucceſs; for Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> upon this returns to the <hi>College;</hi> and accordingly on <hi>Nov.</hi> 13. 1633 he was Pre-elected Fellow <hi>pro Domino fundatore,</hi> of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and thereupon in <hi>Jan.</hi> 28 following he was admitted to the Vacancy of the next Fellowſhip. But that, it ſeems (as Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons often are but airy) did not ſoon fall, and therefore that he might not have a Title without profit, he was elected and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into a Fellowſhip <hi>pro Doctore Goch,</hi> in <hi>June</hi> 24. 1634 which notwithſtanding he would not accept of without a <hi>Salvo jure &amp; intereſſe</hi> in his former Election, leſt it ſhould preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50921:20"/> his Right to a Fellowſhip of the Foundation: To which condition the Maſter and the Fellows willingly conſented. For they who ſo much deſired his company, would not (to enjoy it) ſcruple at any thing which was not inconſiſtent with their Oaths and Statutes. Purſuant of which deſign on <hi>Decemb.</hi> 19 following, they unanimouſly decreed, that his firſt Election and Admiſſion ſhould be ſufficient for him to obtain and enjoy what Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſoever firſt and next vacant, unleſs appropriate to ſome School or Scholarſhip by its Original Foundation. Which Decree ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to four Fellowſhips more than his firſt Admiſſion; a thing ſo uncommon, that I am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from a very good hand, the like inſtance cannot eaſily be met with in that College Books.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50921:20"/>
            <p> We have ſeen Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled in that College, let us in the next place ſee, whether he will anſwer that expectation and hopes which had been conceived of him.</p>
            <p>To underſtand this the better, we will conſider him under a double capacity, as a Preacher, and as a Tutor. As to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe, thô I cannot (as I have already mentioned) find the Time when he entred into Holy Orders; yet I am informed, That after his fixing again in the Univerſity, he preached two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons at S. <hi>Pauls Croſs;</hi> the one in <hi>Sept.</hi> 28. 1634, upon <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27, which he printed at the entreaty of his Friends, and Entituled it, <hi>Labour forbidden and commanded;</hi> and Dedicated the ſame to Sir <hi>John Wray,</hi> Baronet, and his Brother Mr. <hi>Edward Wray:</hi> And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50921:21"/> another in 1639. And in the Univerſity he became a very celebrated Preacher, as he had formerly been highly reſpected for ſome other Exerciſes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by him there in his younger years: For his Sermons before the Univerſity were heard with great applauſe. His Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was always crowded and thronged; and to give you one Inſtance of the great eſteem he had publickly gained as an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Preacher, I need only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that when he who was appointed to Preach in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity Church,</hi> failed to perform that duty, the Vice Chancellor (that then was) earneſtly deſired Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> to ſupply that public Defect; which, thô unwilling to undertake, as having neither any Notes about him, nor time for Premeditation, at laſt through
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50921:21"/> the ſolicitation of that Public perſon he condeſcended to it. And his ready Parts and great Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties enabled him, by Gods Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereon, to perform that difficult Task to ſatisfaction and even admiration, which his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty would have diſſwaded him from attempting.</p>
            <p>This was indeed a Public Trial and Atteſtation of his Worth, and that before ſo Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and Learned a Society; and therefore when in the ſequel of this performance he found himſelf but too apt in Caſes of this nature to be pleaſed and elated with the vain Praiſes (as he ſtyled them) of a frothy Wit, he upon ſerious conſideration with himſelf, finding ſuch <hi>Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums</hi> to be but glittering No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, and no fit Objects for his Contemplation, which ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50921:22"/> not ſix upon any thing but more laſting and ſolid Joys; and begging the Divine Aſſiſtance to the compleating of that pious Deſign, did ſet himſelf to bend his ſtudies another way, thô with much more difficulty and toil to himſelf; ſince thoſe (by him) unaffected Flowers of Rhetoric which appeared, and thoſe ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Rays of Wit which ſhon forth in his firſt Performances at the Univerſity (as well as in the late mentioned Sermon, <hi>Labour forbidden and commanded,)</hi> thô they came to him naturally in a manner, and with much eaſe, did not in his Judgment (at leaſt) tend to the advancement of God's Glory, which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal end of our Nativity; and which, he wiſely and truly judged, ought to be the chief end and deſign of every Sermon.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50921:22"/>
            <p> He did not think, that a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (or rather an Harangue) gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Tropical and Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Flowers, and beautified with gay Similies taken from the Hiſtorians or Poets, could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute much to the ſaving of a Soul. 'Twas not a laboured Oratorial Sentence, a round Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, or a Quaint expreſſion, that could (in his Opinion) much aſſiſt to the compleating of that grand Affair, among the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned. He judged a plainneſs of Matter, a clearneſs and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity of Style, in the expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sacred Oracles of the Old and New Teſtament, and adapting and applying them home to the Conſciences and Spiritual Neceſſities of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Perſons, and that in an eaſie and familiar Language, was the grand deſign of a true Chriſtian
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50921:23"/> Orator, in perſwading his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the love and imitation of the Great Captain of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> to adore him ſincerely here, and to enjoy him eternally hereafter, by our being adopted into that happy number of his Brethren. For the perſwading of one poor Soul, whom our Bleſſed Saviour hath redeemed with his dear Blood, to live as a Chriſtian ought to do, firſt by working upon the Judgment, and then by engaging the Affections, is of an infinite more value than to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the empty glory of being accounted a Chriſtian, a <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes,</hi> or a <hi>Cicero;</hi> to rival in Eloquence a <hi>Lactantius,</hi> a <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom,</hi> or a <hi>Bernard.</hi> And in this method of Preaching did he continue till Death put a Period to his Labours and Toils.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:50921:23"/>
            <p> You have ſeen him in a Public Capacity, as a Preacher; now conſider him in his Private one, as a Tutor.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1635 he begun to take Pupils, which he inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with ſo much care, and by his frequent Lectures, both in the Myſteries of Philoſophy, and in that, to which the other ought always to be ſubſervient, the Fundamentals and neceſſary ſuperſtructure of Religion, as well as by his conſtant inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into their Manners and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, fearing, that otherwiſe, while they peruſed the large Volumes of the ſage and quick-ſighted Heathen Philoſophers, they ſhould forget that they were Chriſtians; and ſhould not remember God, the Firſt Cauſe and Author of all, while they wandred in the Maze and Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50921:24"/> of Second Cauſes; and laſtly, leſt while they dwelt upon the ſtudy of Ethicks, they ſhould contradict the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of their own Religion, by a deplorable Immorality. So that Dr. <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> whom I have had occaſion to mention twice, as his great Friend, pleas'd with his real Induſtry, as well as ſatisfied with his acute Parts, which he had the opportunity of knowing better by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity of his Company, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Care the two Sons of <hi>Theophilus,</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who had been recommended to his own, when at the ſame time another Nobleman, my Lord <hi>Daincourt</hi> had entruſted Mr. <hi>Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow</hi> with the like number. Which Truſt he did ſo far anſwer, that that joyned to the often Viſits he made the Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50921:24"/> the Company of the Earls Sons from <hi>Cambridge,</hi> during the time of that Noble Perſons long affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the racks of the Gout, acquired him not only an high eſteem at that time, but made way for his higher advancement in the Church afterwards, through the Favour and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (I might have added the true Gratitude) of that Noble Family. For the Earl by this means came to have a true knowledge of Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi>'s real worth and from thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted an high value for him, and a Kindneſs proportionable thereto.</p>
            <p>To return again to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> from whence we have been ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a while at <hi>Audley Inn,</hi> 'twas after his Settlement in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that the frequency of his Viſits to Dr. <hi>Smith</hi> occaſioned
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50921:25"/> an Acquaintance and Kindneſs betwixt Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Smith,</hi> Daughter, to the ſaid Worthy Doctor, whoſe Vertues I would have mention'd in this place, if her Modeſty (ſhe being yet alive) did not reſtrain me from doing it, and withal make that Character, I might now give her, look like Flattery in me to her now living; which would be but Juſtice and a debt to her Vertues, when dead. Therefore, to wave this juſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyric, I muſt only add, that then began that vertuous Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betwixt them, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for ſeveral years before it was compleated by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Tye, by reaſon of the Iniquity, and the Threatning of thoſe (to give them a ſoft Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet) Cloudy Times.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50921:25"/>
            <p> In the Year 1639 our Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> was choſen Dean of the College; which Office he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with great care and prudence; diſcouraging and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Vicious, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging the diligent and ſober young Students. Upon the <hi>20th</hi> day of <hi>April</hi> he fell into a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Swoon, ſo that that Day wherein he firſt drew Breath, had like to have proved the day of his death. And hence after his Recovery he had Meditations ſuitable thereto, to be ſeen in his Diary.</p>
            <p>I have already mentioned, what Favour he had gained of the Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> one of whoſe Anceſtors had founded that Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege: Conſequent of the high Opinion that Earl had of Mr. <hi>Rainbows</hi> Integrity, in making a Settlement of his Eſtate in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50921:26"/> Year 1640, he did him the Honour (among other Truſtees) to make him one; as remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring not only how careful a Tutor he was over his Sons, but how happy an Inſtrument he had that year been in reconciling a Difference betwixt himſelf and his Eldeſt Son.</p>
            <p>This great Truſt Mr. <hi>Rainbow,</hi> becauſe young, undertook with ſome unwillingneſs; but he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged it afterwards with all imaginable Fidelity; therein not propoſing to himſelf the leaſt improvement of his own private Fortunes, but the Advantage of that Noble Family. And, while he continued therein after the death of Earl <hi>Theophilus,</hi> which happened in <hi>June</hi> in the Year laſt mentioned, thô his Care for the Eſtate of his Honourable Charge was great, yet was it no
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50921:26"/> leſs for the great Concern of their Souls, without which the other had been leſs valuable; and over whom, agreeable to his Function, he was very watchful and diligent; and God was not wanting to bleſs his Pious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours therein with a ſuitable Return. Which Happineſs was not confined to thoſe Noble Youths he had under his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Tuition, but extended to other young Perſons of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, who frequented that Family. For he obſerving ſome Extravagancies in them, too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to men of their Figure, and who meet with many Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and eſpecially with one, that of Flattery, the bane of Youth, wrought ſo upon their Spirits by his cogent Reaſons, and inſinuating Rhetoric, that they gratefully accepted of ſome
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50921:27"/> Prayers compoſed by Mr. <hi>Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow,</hi> which were ſuited to their particular condition, as was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent by ſome Papers ſeen after his death. And thoſe Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons had ever afterwards a juſt veneration and a true kindneſs for him. Hence became he ſo much the Favourite of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of <hi>Suffolk, Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Warwick,</hi> and <hi>Orrery.</hi> And ſince I have mentioned the laſt, I cannot forbear to add, that he who firſt bore that Title, hath in his Divine Poems, which he wrote in his declining years, bating the difference of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, outſtript thoſe of <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius</hi> (who alſo compoſed his in his old Age) in the richneſs of Fancy, and in delicacy of Expreſſion. And as he had in other Topics (compoſed for his diverſion) ſhewn, that he wanted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50921:27"/> not a chaſt and elegant Style, even when he treated on leſs ſevere and ſerious Subjects; ſo hath he in thoſe his Poems on the Feſtivals acquired a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which will never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd his Merit till Wit and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be exil'd the World, no more than Poſterity can without the higeſt Injuſtice refuſe the Title of a moſt acurate Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Philoſopher to his yet ſurviving Brother, and our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Friend, the Honourable Mr. <hi>Robert Boyle;</hi> a Gentleman, who is no leſs happy in, and reſpected for a ſweetneſs of Temper, than for his Ingenuity. And the preſent Age ſeems ſo much in love with his Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Experiments, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes upon them, by which he hath ſignalized himſelf to the greateſt part of <hi>Europe,</hi> that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50921:28"/> even a Critic of another Nation, not very ready to beſtow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements upon others; but when even compelled thereto by Truth, cannot deny, but that his Experiments and Reflexions have always an Air of Solidity. To which may be juſtly added, that as he hath enriched Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy with his choice Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations; ſo hath he, in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the trite Objection of ſuch Students, being near Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to Atheiſts, made that dear Miſtreſs an Handmaid to Religion. But I now forget, that I treſpaſs againſt the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Patience by this long digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as well as hereby offend this Religious Gentlemans Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty; for which, after I have craved pardon of both, I ſhall return to Mr. <hi>Rainbow;</hi> whom we ſhall (according to the Series
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50921:28"/> of his Hiſtory) find ready to attend the young Earl of <hi>Suffolk, James,</hi> to the Long Parliament in <hi>October</hi> 1640. A Parliament, a ſmall part of which afterwards, under the ſpecious pretence of a thorough Reformation, brought one of the beſt of our Kings, <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, to the Block, and laid waſte that Church of <hi>England,</hi> which hath been long the Glory and Bulwark (under God) of the Reformed Religion, and the Envy of the Romiſh.</p>
            <p>In 1642 Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> had the Honour to Marry the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Algernoon</hi> Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> to the Lady <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Howard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His great Friend, Dr. <hi>Henry Smith</hi> dying, and the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Magdalen</hi> College be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thereby vacant, in <hi>October</hi> 1642, Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50921:29"/> had a Promiſe and Grant of that Place upon the firſt vacancy from the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Theophilus</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> was now admitted into it with the concurrence of his Son, Earl <hi>James.</hi> And now ſeeing himſelf ſet upon an higher ground, and conſequently his Actions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by expoſed more to the Public view and cenſure, his next and chief Care was to diſcharge his new Truſt conſcientiouſly; and therefore having, while he was a Fellow of that ſame College, taken notice, that ſome very hopeful young Men had, upon their being too early Advanc'd, fallen from their former ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vertuous courſe of living into Debauchery; He, upon his acceſſion to the Maſterſhip, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to admit any man to a Fellowſhip, who had not firſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50921:29"/> commenced Mr. of Arts; that their longer ſtay before their Preferment might give the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege a clearer demonſtration of their Worth, and they thereby might become (as it were) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationers for three Years.</p>
            <p>He took the Degree of Dr. of Divinity in the Year 1646, when his chief Queſtion (on which he made his <hi>Theſis)</hi> was, That <hi>Eccleſia Anglicana tenet omnia ad ſalutem neceſſaria.</hi> A Point which he durſt defend in the worſt of Times, when that Church was ſo much oppreſs'd, for aſſerting her Loyalty to God and the King; for her agreement with the Primitive Church in not rebelling againſt a lawful Magiſtrate, and in owning the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of the Epiſcopal Hierarchy and Liturgy.</p>
            <p>But that Black Storm, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50921:30"/> (occaſioned by the Sins of this Nation, then ſurfeiting of Eaſe and Plenty) was permitted a while to hover over our Heads in Black Clouds, broke out at laſt in dreadful Thunders upon our Trembling <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and tore down all that oppos'd its way. In this common Calamity Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> had his ſhare both by ſympathizing with the Loſſes of others, and by his particular Sufferings.</p>
            <p>The Royal Martyrs death was that, which in a terrible manner opened the Eyes of all thoſe who before would not, or could not ſee, that under the Maſque of <hi>Piety, Rebellion</hi> Lorded it over Loyalty; when one of the moſt horrid Villanies, that the Sun ever ſaw in this Nation, was perpetrated in open Day! A Pious King, and one who held his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50921:30"/> Crown of none, but his Great Creator, firſt haled to a Tribunal, (an Act not to be paralleld in all preceding Ages) who when he had juſtly deny'd that Uſurped Power before whom he was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven'd; after he had ſuffered all the Indignities that the deluded Rabble, and the ruder Souldiery could throw upon him, was Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed upon a Scaffold pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely erected before his own Palace. An Act ſo heinous, that it could not be equalled by any thing, but by the Malice of His Majeſties Enemies, from whom it had its Original.</p>
            <p>In the fall of this tall Cedar, the other Trees of our Foreſt were rudely ſhaken, and thô they were not all hewn down by the fatal Ax, yet were they ſore cut; their Boughs and Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at leaſt lopt off, unleſs that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50921:31"/> ſome of the Shrubs eſcaped, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Lowneſs excuſed them from the Levelling Stroke.</p>
            <p>Thus ſeveral Perſons truly Noble, both for Deſcent and proper Merit, attended their moſt Gracious Sovereign in his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, even to his Fall and their Death; whoſe greateſt Crime was that, for which diſintereſted Poſterity will have them in the higheſt admiration, their Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Becauſe they could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Uſurpations in the Civil Government, and to Innovations in the Eccleſiaſtical, they muſt be Martyrs; or taught to obey in that new way of Goſpelling by Pike, Gun, and Dragoons.</p>
            <p>This, among many other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, was the Fate of our Dr. <hi>Rainbow,</hi> who, for refuſing a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt the King in 1650, loſt his Maſterſhip of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50921:31"/> 
               <hi>Magdalen,</hi> which he had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto kept by the powerful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nterceſſion of his Noble Friends; and which he was very willing to ſacrifice, rather than to make a Sacrifice of his Conſcience to thoſe <hi>Anakims,</hi> which had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Entitle them to the Government, but Violence and Rapin.</p>
            <p>He had been a Mourner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this, in the general loſs of the Nation, in the horrid Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Gracious Sovereign, and was a particular one in the Interment of that truly Religious Lady, the Lady <hi>Suſanna,</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Suffolk;</hi> the Hiſtory of whoſe Vertues is far from being Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal. Nor did ſhe want a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hiſtorian in Doctor <hi>Edward Rainbow,</hi> who in <hi>May</hi> 13. 1649. made her Funeral Sermon in a pathetical and moving Air;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50921:32"/> but did it as far from Flattery, as ſhe was above it; ſince he ſpoke nothing but what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, and was not her Orator to preſent her Vertues in a gaudy Dreſs, but her faithful Hiſtorian, to deliver what he knew upon good grounds to be true.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> being exiled from <hi>Magdalen</hi> College, by the Order of the Rump Parliament, which College now became a Mourner for loſing her Orthodox Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, was Preſented by the Earl of <hi>Suffolk</hi> to a ſmall Living a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> little <hi>Cheſterford,</hi> near <hi>Audley Inn</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in 1652, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, when he ſaw no proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of that dark Cloud's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing, which ſtill hung ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this then diſtemper'd Nation.</p>
            <p>But he, who had loſt the Maſterſhip of a College for his Loyalty, was reſolved not to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50921:32"/> ſtain his Conſcience by a baſe ſubmiſſion to thoſe Uſurpers, in the acceptance of that place; and therefore held it only by my Lord of <hi>Suffolk</hi>'s Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without being ſetled therein according to the prevalency of thoſe Licentious Times by their Tryers. In which privacy, ſince we have found him ſetled, we will ſee how he manages in that Critical Juncture; after I have ſubjoyned, That it was in this Year of 1652 that he married Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Smith,</hi> his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors Daughter; who (without Flattery I ſpeak it) were ſo happy in each other, that thoſe who had the longeſt Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with them, never heard an harſh Word fall from them againſt each other: A Felicity rarely to be found! and which ought to be mentioned to their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50921:33"/> Honour; and which doubtleſs was a true ſign, that they were both unfeigned Votaries to Vertue.</p>
            <p>In this his Receſs, a place much more agreeable to his Inclination than Merit, did Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> continue for ſome years. And, thô he was ſo far retired from the Noiſe and Buſtles of thoſe Tumultuous Times; yet he knew he could not retire out of the piercing Eye of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, with whom he had to do. He knew, it was as much incumbent upon him to do his duty there, as in a more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous ſtation; and therefore, thô he could not openly uſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy, yet he uſed ſome of thoſe excellent Prayers of which it is compos'd; and that not only in his private Family, but alſo compoſed ſuch Prayers as he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50921:33"/> uſed in the Church out of thoſe in the Liturgy; and ſo gradually brought the Ignorant People to affect the Common Prayers, a little transformed and altered; who diſliked the Common Prayer Book it ſelf, they knew not why.</p>
            <p>Nor was he ſatisfied with his own Practice alone in this Caſe; when therefore he lodged one Night at a Clergyman's Houſe, an old Acquaintance of his, who then uſed other Prayers in his Family, he out of civility to him commended his Friends form of Prayer; but adviſed him for the future to uſe the Prayers of the Church, for there were none other like them.</p>
            <p>Nor did this Pious Doctor look upon his conſtant Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be a ſufficient diſcharge of his duty, and that which would ſerve to clear him when
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50921:34"/> he was to give an account of his Stewardſhip to his great Maſter. He believd, That many of his Hearers came to Church purely out of Cuſtom and Form, and conſequently that their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was not very profitable and advantagious to their Souls, in minding what was delivered to them from the Pulpit, and therefore often went to their Houſes to Catechiſe and inſtruct them, and to thoſe who were indigent he often gave Mony to oblige them to attend to his Inſtructions; thereby making their Temporal. Neceſſities to contribute to the ſupplying their Spiritual Wants. A double Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity! for which, I doubt not, he hath long ſince met with a double reward from the Liberal Diſpenſer of all good things.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:50921:34"/>
            <p> In this place did our Dr. <hi>Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow</hi> reſide, pleaſed with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition, and his Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners no leſs pleaſed with him, till <hi>April</hi> 1659, when the Rectory of <hi>Benefield</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> valued at 200 <hi>l.</hi> or 300 <hi>l. per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and of the Gift of the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> fell Vacant, and was profered him by the ſaid Noble Earl; which he utterly refuſed, becauſe the Tryers, with whom he was reſolved to have nothing to do, were then in power; till there was ſent him a Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> with an Aſſurance, That he might be poſſeſt of <hi>Benefield</hi> without going to the Tryers. Which laſt Favour had been procured him by the Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> then only Lord <hi>Broghil,</hi> and both out of the reſpect which thoſe Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſonages had to his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50921:35"/> Worth and ſweet Temper.</p>
            <p>Having (thô very unwilling to leave his Retirement at <hi>Cheſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford)</hi> accepted of the Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Benefield,</hi> upon the above-mentioned Conditions; wherein by the by the Reader may ſee, how careful he was not to make Shipwreck of a good Conſcience for any Temporal Benefit or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, he managed things there as he had done at <hi>Little Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterford,</hi> compoſing all his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the Church out of the Liturgy; which being repeated by him at the Offices of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening, Burial, &amp;c. by Heart, which the Ignorant People not underſtanding, liked well. And there he lived with great content, and in quietneſs; being kindly treated by that People, who roughly treated others of the ſame Function.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:50921:35"/>
            <p> Before, in the courſe of our Hiſtory, I come to that Great and happy year of 1660, when our late Sovereign, <hi>CHARLES the Merciful,</hi> was reſtored with the joyful Acclamations of all his Loving Subjects to his Crown and Dignity, and his Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to their Privileges, Laws and Religion, I am to inform the Reader, That Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> had the ſatisfaction to hear, as the Nation had to know, that <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> put a Period to the ſitting of that Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which had ruined three Kingdoms, and unhinged the whole Royal Family, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Reform the firſt. And this was done after they had ſat about Twelve years, in 1653, on that very day in which Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> was born. A Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, at which he not only
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50921:36"/> publickly rejoyced, becauſe it happened on the Day of his Nativity; but he alſo noted it in his Diary, with a Prayer, <hi>That God would turn it to the good of the Church and Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed: In the Year 1660, when the Finger of God ſignally appeared in bringing, in this our Nation, a King to the Throne of his Royal Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, after Twelve years Exile, and without a Stroke ſtruck, notwithſtanding that there was a Veteran Army, fluſhed in Blood and Victory, and trained up in an averſion to Monarchy then in being, the Church was alſo reſtored with the King. And then all thoſe Worthy Perſons, who in the preceding Times of Rebellion and Confuſion had been Sufferers by loſs of Goods or Places, or by Impriſonment,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50921:36"/> or by Baniſhment, were either reſtored to the places which they had formerly poſſeſſed, or were preferred to higher Honours. Among others, Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> was reſtored to his Maſterſhip of <hi>Magdalen</hi> College, and by the favour and ſolicitation of his Noble Friends was made Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to his late Majeſty, King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second; and in the Year following was made Dean of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> where he had formerly been a Scholar.</p>
            <p>Thither he removed in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1661, with a deſign to reſide there; but his ſtay there was not long, Preferments coming now thick upon him. For he was the next Year called to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> being elected Vice Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of that famous Univerſity in <hi>Nov.</hi> 1662. Which early Election of him to that great Truſt, was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50921:37"/> not only a public Teſtimony of the Univerſities great eſteem for him, but of his Loyalty too</p>
            <p>In the diſcharge of the Vice-Chancellors Office he acquitted himſelf with ſufficient Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the management thereof forgot not the Care and Intereſt of that College, whereof he was the Head. For whereas the Office of a Proctor came not to that College in 44 Years, he got it to be publickly ordered and confirmed by His late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that that Office ſhould return to <hi>Magdalen</hi> College every Ninth Year; and by a Politic fixing the <hi>Epocha</hi> of this new Circle, got a Courſe to his own College ſooner than it could expect. And not only ſo, but becauſe ſome who were put up to Preach in the Univerſity Church, got for a ſmall ſum of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50921:37"/> Mony others to do it for them, who performed it ſo meanly, that it turn'd often to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof; to prevent which, he procured a Mulct of 40 <hi>s.</hi> to be impoſed on every ſuch Offender, and to give a good Example therein to the Maſters of Art, the Heads of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges (by his inſtigation) yielded to Preach there in their Turns.</p>
            <p>And now being fix'd again in his former ſtation, with the additional Revenue of the Dean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> he had more than ſatisfi'd his Ambition, which never aim'd higher than ſuch a ſtation, as wherein he might live decently, and might be capacitated to be ſerviceable to his Country. But, beyond his Wiſhes, no leſs than above his Expectation, was he Elected Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle</hi> in 1664, upon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50921:38"/> the Tranſlation of the Right Reverend Dr. <hi>Richard Stern</hi> to the Archiepiſcopal See of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This new Advancement was directly contrary to his mind, as he declared it to thoſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Friends of his, who had therein ſolicited for him. His truly Primitive temper put him upon the declining of that high and honourable Employment in the Church; the great Care of ſo many Souls, as would thereby be devolved upon him, affrighted and deterr'd him a while from embracing that Honour, which ſo many court in vain, who ſo little know how to diſcharge it. He look'd upon himſelf, as did the Ancient Fathers, to be unfit for that High Calling; which was, thô in his Judgment, highly honourable, yet withal a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then too heavy for his weak
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50921:38"/> Shoulders to bear and ſuſtain. He was deſirous, as our Moſt Reverend and Learned Primate, Archbiſhop <hi>Parker,</hi> was in the laſt Age, to be ſerviceable to the Church, thô moving in a lower Sphere, and only that he might enjoy thoſe Promotions and Dignities he had then arrived to, without aſcending higher.</p>
            <p>Thus meanly did he think of himſelf (what others often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted him in) as not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently qualified for that high Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and had ſtill refuſed it, if the Importunity of his Friends had not at laſt prevailed with him to decline it no longer. And there was one thing which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed not a little to his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of it; the great reſpect which he had for two ancient and very deſerving Friends, which upon his removal to <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſle</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:50921:39"/> were to ſucceed him in his preſent Promotions; the one in his Deanry, and the other in his Maſterſhip.</p>
            <p>Overcome at laſt with the Deſires and Arguments of his Friends, he accepted of that Honourable Dignity, that was procured him by his Noble Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons Mediation; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly was Conſecrated in <hi>July</hi> 1664, at <hi>London,</hi> by the Moſt Reverend Father in God, Dr. <hi>Gilbert Sheldon,</hi> then Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and came to ſettle at <hi>Roſe Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Palace for the Biſhops of that See, on <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. following.</p>
            <p>I ought to mention, That his generoſity in this Caſe was ſo great, that thô (perhaps) he was at that time in ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as to need ſome aſſiſtance to defray the neceſſary Charges
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50921:39"/> of his Conſecration, Firſt-Fruits, and his Journy to, and Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Dioceſs; yet did not he ſo much as deſire to hold the Maſterſhip of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege in <hi>Commendam</hi> for a while with his Biſhoprick; but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently and freely reſigned both that Place and his Deanry of <hi>Peterborough</hi> to his Succeſſors in them both; althô ſuch Favours as the retaining one of them for ſome time, had not unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally been granted to others upon the like Promotion.</p>
            <p>We have now ſeen him aſcend by Steps into the Epiſcopal Throne; a Dignity which the Primitive Church of Chriſt had ſo great a Veneration for, and which in Times of hot Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution had been ſo often ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Blood of thoſe who ſat thereon; they exchanging
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50921:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> that tickliſh Honour for an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Crown of Glory, by that of Martyrdom, we will now take a ſtand, and view how he diſcharges that Sacred Office.</p>
            <p>He found his Palace at <hi>Roſe-Caſtle</hi> much ruinated; a great part of it being burnt down by the Rebels in the late times of Rebellion, and but little Repaired by his immediate Predeceſſor; thô he had receiv'd great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages by entring upon that Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick after ſo long a Vacancy, and the Expiration of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants Leaſes, which engaged him in a Suit about Dilapidations with his Predeceſſor, then his Metropolitan. In which Trouble he was unwillingly embark'd, as that which was both repugnant to his Meek Nature, and was (in his Thoughts) unbecoming Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of that Sacred Character.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50921:40"/>
            <p> After the concluſion of that long Suit, he was at great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in Building at <hi>Roſe-Caſtle,</hi> for he built the Chapel anew, and made ſeveral other Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Conveniences there.</p>
            <p>But thô theſe Edifices were Coſtly as well as Troubleſom; yet there was another ſort of Building which he was more intent upon, the Building of God's Church in the Spiritual ſenſe; and that, either by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or his Aſſiſtants, his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the Clergy, in the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Preaching of Gods Word; in the due Adminiſtration of the Holy Sacraments; in Catechiſing of Youth, (which word is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by ſome Grammarians, <hi>To build up in the Holy Faith;)</hi> in adviſing them to walk in the Paths of Vertue and Holineſs, and in admoniſhing and reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50921:41"/> the more Looſe from their Immoralities.</p>
            <p>As this was his great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; ſo was it his deſire and endeavour to ſee, that the Clergy ſubordinate to him ſhould do their Duties. In the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which, when ſome who had been ſufficiently Criminal and Neglectful in the diſcharge of their Function, were juſtly reproved by him for ſo doing; thô that was done too at the firſt with Meekneſs enough, yet he met with a very rude Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from them, and much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming their ſtation; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs both that and the Ill Returns made him from perſons whom he had highly obliged, was far from making him Vindictive, if his public Character and the intereſt of the Church were not interwoven with his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50921:41"/> For then he would take care to reſcue both from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, leſt the Common Cauſe might ſuffer by his own ſupine Negligence. I ſhall not here revive the remembrance of thoſe Affronts to that Sacred Order by particularizing thoſe which were offered to him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will forbear to mention the offending Perſons Names, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Faults of ſome of them may be buried in the ſame Graves with their Authors; and only add, That generally the Troubles which befel him after his advancement to the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Authority, were occaſioned by his Conſcientious diſcharge of that Sacred Office; which doth not ſeldom make the beſt of Men fall under the weight of popular Odium. For, althô I am far from pretending to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50921:42"/> exempt him in his Management of that Dignity from Miſtakes and Errors, and 'tis certain his own Humility taught him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leſſon, than to aſpire to the ſwelling Title of <hi>Infallible;</hi> yet generally his Failings were ſuch as might admit of an eaſie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, without the aſſiſtance of Political Refinings, to which he was very much a Stranger.</p>
            <p>But to return from whence I have digreſſed: As he inſpected the Lives and Manners of his Clergy, and their performance of their Paſtoral Charge; ſo was not he wanting to ſet them a good Pattern himſelf, being aſſured, that nothing won more upon the Minds and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Men than a good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, eſpecially in thoſe who attend at Gods Altar, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe his Holy Word, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50921:42"/> the Sacred Myſteries of our holy Religion. He therefore reſoved to ſet them a Copy as legible as his human Frailties would permit it to be written, that they fairly imitating it, the Laity might be invited to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it from them.</p>
            <p>Purſuant of his Pious deſign, he Preached not only in his Courſes at the Cathedral, but often there alſo upon occaſional days; as alſo frequently at his own Chappel at <hi>Roſs,</hi> at <hi>Dalſton</hi> Church, and the adjacent Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, till hindred from this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance by the Gout; the Racks of which were not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably more troubleſom than their Conſequence; his being thereby forc'd to omit his Public Duty. And Catechiſing he ſo much kept up, that to oblige ſome indigent Perſons to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50921:43"/> attend it, to their own Spiritual advantage, and the building themſelves in the moſt Holy Faith, he gave them Mony. Neither was his Hoſpitality, offending againſt the Canons of the Church; but like that of a Biſhop. His Entertainment was free; his Table was well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Varieties; his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation pleaſant and yet grave, divertive and yet inſtructing; often feeding the Minds, as well as the Bodies of his Gueſts.</p>
            <p>We have obſerved his way of Procedure as to what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the Church; now the ordering of his Family chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges our next Conſideration.</p>
            <p>The Government of his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Family was modelled in imitation of that of the Church; that is, Regular. Four times a day was God publickly call'd
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50921:43"/> upon by Prayers in that Family; twice in the Chappel, which part his Lordſhips Chaplains perform'd; and twice in the Dining-Room; the later of theſe at Six in the Morning and Nine at Night, was the uſual Task of our Right Reverend and Worthy Prelate himſelf, if not diſabled by Sickneſs. As if he who was the Maſter of the Family, would open it every Morning, and lock it up every Night, by the Key of Prayer.</p>
            <p>All known Profaneſs and Swearing were baniſhed thence: For this made as much diſcord in that Family, as an ill Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian did in <hi>Plato</hi>'s Schools. Offenders in Debauchery were at firſt reproved and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and if they relapſed into the ſame Fault, they were often diſmiſs'd the Houſe; unleſs
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50921:44"/> there appeared viſible ſigns of Repentance, and thoſe uſhered in with fervent Promiſes, to make thoſe good by their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours.</p>
            <p>While the Suit was continued betwixt the then Archbiſhop of <hi>Tork</hi> and our Worthy Prelate, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Year 1668, he was once offered to be removed from the See of <hi>Carliſle</hi> to that of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> by the moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God <hi>Gilbert Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> A Prelate, who, beſides the Monuments he erected to his Name by his truly primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Vertues, hath left one at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that famous Theatre built at his own charge, and dedicated to the uſes of the Public, the ſervice of the Church, and the Muſes. A Structure, which (if the World laſt ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50921:44"/> long) may continue the Name of that Pious Archbiſhop longer than the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Pyramids, have continued the memory of their ambitious and vainglorious Founders.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> liſtned with ſome pleaſure to that Motion of the good Archbiſhop, as being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be freed from the Inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes which his legal Diſpute with his Metropolitan in the above-mentioned Caſe of Dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidations did create him. But herein he met with too potent an Adverſary to be ſucceſsful; a great Lady, with whom he had formerly had ſome acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and a juſt reſpect: But, when ſhe had forfeited his Eſteem, and that of all good Men, by the proſtitution of her Honour, our good Biſhop did not then think himſelf obliged,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50921:45"/> notwithſtanding her greater Quality, to pay her thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards he had formerly done. And when ſhe, after that, offered him Civilities, he was ſo far from laying hold on ſuch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to advance his Fortunes by her mediation, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined her very Company; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the moſt innocent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of ſuch a Perſon, who had forgotten her Noble practices in the addition of new Titles, and thoſe purchaſed at a dear rate with the loſs of her Fame.</p>
            <p>This ſlight from our pious Prelate, the Lady ſo highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, that partly out of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Pique, and partly out of a deſign to prefer an Uncle of hers to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> thò far unfit to be placed in ſo much Light, ſhe hindered the Tranſlation of Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:50921:45"/> thither. Albeit the pious Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop ſo far prevailed over that Ladies Intereſt as to get an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Biſhop, deſigned before for <hi>Carliſle,</hi> and with the thoughts whereof he had been well enough contented, to be placed in the ſtead of that Ladies Uncle, who was thereby gently laid aſide.</p>
            <p>Our Prelate was not much diſpleas'd at this turn of Aſſairs, thò he had wiſhed the contrary for the above-mentioned Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; to which another might be added, That the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi>'s Palace at <hi>Bugden</hi> was ſo ſituated as to be near <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and not far diſtant from <hi>London;</hi> in which reſpect he could not have wiſhed to have been better fixed than there, for the enjoyment of his Relations and intimate Acquaintance; yet
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50921:46"/> when he firſt conſidered in his cooler, by whoſe intereſt he was fruſtrated of his expectations; and that the Biſhoprick of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> beſides its vaſt extent, which ſtill increaſed the Cure of Souls, and conſequently made that greater burthen ballance the greater Revenue, it had (as he thought) a greater inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, that that Revenue, ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the other of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> (which notwithſtanding was far from tempting our Prelate to a removal to <hi>Lincoln)</hi> conſiſted much in Penſions from the Clergy; ſo that he uſed to ſay, That <hi>that Biſhop was maintained out of the poor Clergy mans Mouths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Edward Rainbow</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued nigh Twenty years in the exerciſe of his Epiſcopal Function, thô often indiſpoſed,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50921:46"/> and eſpecially in his later years, with the <hi>Stone</hi> and the <hi>Gout;</hi> two Diſeaſes of ſo acute a pain, that they would not only poſe the patience, or rather pretended apathy of the proudeſt Stoical Philoſopher, but put even a Chriſtian one to fly from Second Cauſes to the Firſt of all, for his ſupport under that torment, more cruel than the diſpatching and devouring Flames; He had been Biſhop, I ſay ſo long, when in <hi>March</hi> 1683. his Pains occaſioned (as was ſuppoſed) by the Gout in the Stomach, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed; and the more they augmented, the more did our Pious Biſhop apply himſelf to the Phyſician of Souls, as looking upon the Bodily health to be in a declining condition; albeit, to preſerve it, he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected not to conſult Phyſicians
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50921:47"/> for the Body too, but in vain.</p>
            <p>When he was therefore aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that Death was approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, with how much chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and with what a true Chriſtian Magnanimity did he look the King of Terrors in the Face! He prepared to receive him, not as an Enemy, but as a welcom Friend, who was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct him out of this Vale of Tears, into the Manſions of Eternal Joy, far above all the Regions of Inſtability. He ſaw his Courſe was almoſt finiſhed, and he longed to be at the Goal.</p>
            <p>During this his laſt Sickneſs, not one idle or impertinent word fell from him. He had in his Life-time, before this laſt Arreſt of his Body by Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, learned a perfect reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelf to the Divine
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50921:47"/> Will and Pleaſure of Almighty God, and therefore received the approaches of Death with that humble ſubmiſſion to the Divine Will, and with that calmneſs and ſerenity of mind, which are not often found but in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of a Primitive Piety.</p>
            <p>He had indeed begged of God, that he might over-live <hi>Lady-day,</hi> becauſe it would much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the Proſit of his then Conſort, and ſince Mournful Widow. And this ſeems to have been granted to him, ſince he ſurvived the Return of that time no more than one day. Another Petition he alſo made, That his Reaſon and Senſes might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the laſt moment of his Life; which was alſo granted; evidencing thereby, That he was no mean Favourite in the High Court of Heaven: For he lived
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50921:48"/> till Wedneſday, <hi>March</hi> 26. 1684. in the Evening; and yet did he not miſpend his precious Hours. His care for Secular concerns, which was never ſo great as to merit the Title of Fondneſs, was now taken off by a more preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and laudable one; and that which was to be entertained in the preparation for, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of a Future and Eternal ſtate. Hence the laſt Moments wherein he enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the uſe of his Tongue were ſpent in a moſt Pious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Prudent Counſel to thoſe that were about him; Holy Meditations upon his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition at that time; fervent Prayers and Supplications to the King of Mercy, were the happy employments of his Heavenly Soul; and all theſe performed with ſo much zeal and fervour,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50921:48"/> that it ſeem'd already to be upon the Wing towards Heaven.</p>
            <p>Towards Even, on Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day above-mentioned, being got into Bed, and finding himſelf very weak, he called for Prayers; which being concluded, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his Speech to fail, he ſpake theſe Words to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany which were then with him: <hi>It hath pleaſed God to take away my Speech, and I am heavy and dull; I deſire you all to Pray for me, That God would aſſiſt me with his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this he lay quietly, and ſlumbred ſometimes, till Eleven a Clock at Night, when a ſtarting Fit (which formerly in his Sickneſs had troubled him at times) ſeiz'd him ſharply for ſome time; then he lay quietly a while, thô ſenſible (as might be perceived) to the laſt, and ſo
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50921:49"/> breathed out his laſt Breath; yielding up his Spirit to God, the Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of it, and leaving all the Spectators of this his happy End, diſſolv'd in Tears at this long Separation, in going to inherit, I hope, a Crown of Glory, which God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all them which unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly love and ſincerely ſerve him.</p>
            <p>Thus dy'd that Right Reverend and Pious Prelate, Dr. <hi>Edward Rainbow,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> about Eleven of the Clock at Night, on Wedneſday <hi>March</hi> 26. 1684. at the Age of near Seventy ſix years, and was Interred on Tueſday following in <hi>Dalſton</hi> Church yard, <hi>April</hi> 1. 1684. as he had deſired upon his Death-bed. His Herſe was attended with a great multitude of the Gentry, the Clergy, and other
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50921:49"/> Neighbours; Mr. <hi>Thomas Tullie,</hi> his Lordſhips Chaplain and Chancellor of the Dioceſs of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> Preaching his Funeral Sermon.</p>
            <p>As he had requeſted, That no Pomp nor State ſhould be uſed at his Funeral, no more than any <hi>Elogium</hi> ſhould be made of him (ſuch was his rare Modeſty and Humility:) So did he deſire to be buried in <hi>Dalſton</hi> Church-yard, and to have a plain Stone laid over his Grave with no other Inſcription, but that ſuch a Day and Year died <hi>Edward,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which accordingly was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Theſe his two laſt Requeſts are a declaration to the World in his laſt Moments, how little he valued the Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry of Funeral Pomp, and all Monuments, which were not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50921:50"/> built upon the ſure and firm Baſis of Piety.</p>
            <p>We have now ſeen him laid in the Chambers of the Duſt, let us draw the Curtains about him, leaving his Body to repoſe till the laſt Trumpet ſhall awake him to the general Reſurrection of the Juſt.</p>
            <p>He left no Works in Print, but three occaſional Sermons; the two former of which are ſcarce to be got.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe Sermons, and which hath been already twice mentioned, was Preached at S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Croſs,</hi> on <hi>Sept.</hi> 28. 1634, Entituled, <hi>Labour forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and commanded;</hi> and which to all Perſons that peruſe it without prejudice will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evince, That the late Dr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> could cloath his Thoughts in all the gaiety of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50921:50"/> expreſſion ſuitable to a great Audience, when he judged it convenient.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of <hi>Suſanna,</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> Preached <hi>May</hi> 13. 1649. on <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 1. which was printed together with ſome <hi>Elogies</hi> in praiſe of that Vertuous young Lady; which were compoſed by his two intimate and no leſs Learned Friends, Dr. <hi>S. Collins, Regius</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Dr. <hi>James Duport, Greek</hi> Profeſſor there, and his Succeſſor, in the Maſterſhip of <hi>Magdalen</hi> and Deanry of <hi>Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third was Preached at the Interment of <hi>Anne</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Pembroke, Dorſet</hi> and <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery,</hi> at <hi>Appleby</hi> in <hi>Weſtmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, April</hi> 14. 1676. with ſome Remarks on the Life of that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50921:51"/> Eminenr Lady, on <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 1.</p>
            <p>In his Youth he had a rich Vein in Poeſy, in which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſomewhat of <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Air and Fancy, tempered with the Judgment of <hi>Virgil;</hi> but none of his Poetical Exerciſes and Diverſions have been publiſhed, but a Paper of Verſes upon the Frontiſpiece of Mr. <hi>Henry Iſaac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Chronology; which acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Chronologer was our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops particular Friend, and had formerly been <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> to that living Library, while he was alive, the Reverend and Learned Biſhop <hi>Andrews;</hi> and another Paper on Mr. <hi>Shelton</hi>'s Art of Short-Writing.</p>
            <p>Of the Honour of the former of theſe Poems, printed without the addition of any Name in 1633, he was robbed by the Publiſher of Mr. <hi>Richard Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi>'s
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50921:51"/> Poems, Entituled, <hi>Steps to the Temple,</hi> and aſcribed by him to that Ingenious <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grammatiſt.</hi> But he having no Title to it, but what the modeſt ſilence of Mr. <hi>Rainbow</hi> gave him, I have recovered it to the true Owner by a <hi>Melius inquiren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> and ſubjoyned it here.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Frontiſpiece of Mr.</hi> Iſaacſon<hi>'s Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology explain'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>IF with diſtinctive Eye and Mind, you look</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Front, you ſee more than one Book.</l>
               <l>Creation is God's Book, wherein he writ it.</l>
               <l>Each Creature as a Letter filling</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:50921:52"/>
               <l> Hiſtory is Creation's Book; which ſhews,</l>
               <l>To what effect the Series of it goes.</l>
               <l>Chronology is the Book of Hiſtory, and bears</l>
               <l>The juſt Account of Days, and Months, and Years:</l>
               <l>But Reſurrection in a later Preſs,</l>
               <l>And New Edition is the ſum of theſe.</l>
               <l>The Language of theſe Books had all been one,</l>
               <l>Had not th' aſpiring Tower of <hi>Babylon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Confus'd the Tongues, and in a diſtance hurl'd</l>
               <l>As far the Speech, as Men o'th' New-found World.</l>
               <l>Set then your Eyes in method, and behold</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Time</hi>'s Emblem, <hi>Saturn;</hi> who, when ſtore of Gold</l>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:50921:52"/>
               <l> Coyn'd the firſt Age, devour'd that Birth, he fear'd,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Hiſtory, Time</hi>'s Eldeſt Child appear'd,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phoenix-like,</hi> in ſpight of <hi>Saturn</hi>'s Rage,</l>
               <l>Forc'd from her Aſhes, Heirs in every Age;</l>
               <l>From th' Riſing Sun, obtaining by juſt Suit</l>
               <l>A <hi>Spring</hi>'s Ingender, and an <hi>Autumn</hi>'s Fruit.</l>
               <l>Who in thoſe Volumes at her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Penn'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto <hi>Creation</hi>'s <hi>Alpha</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</l>
               <l>Again aſcend, and view <hi>Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By Optic Skill pulling far, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</l>
               <l>Nearer; whoſe hand the piercing Eagles Eye</l>
               <l>Strengthens, to bring remoteſt Objects nigh:</l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:50921:53"/>
               <l> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder whoſe Feet you ſee the Setting <hi>Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the dark <hi>Gnomon,</hi> o're her Volumes run,</l>
               <l>Drown'd in Eternal Night, never to riſe,</l>
               <l>Till Reſurrection ſhew it to the Eyes</l>
               <l>Of Earth-worn Men; and her ſhrill Trumpets ſound</l>
               <l>Affright the Bones of Mortals from the Ground.</l>
               <l>The Columns both are Crown'd with either Sphere,</l>
               <l>To ſhew <hi>Chronology</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory</hi> bear</l>
               <l>No other <hi>Culmen,</hi> than the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Art,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſtronomy, Geography</hi> impart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:50921:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Another POEM, upon Mr.</hi> Shelton<hi>'s Art of Short-Writing.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">To the Author, his Friend, upon his Art of Short-Writing.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FOrtunate Art, by which the Hand ſo ſpeeds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That Words are now of ſlower birth than Deeds!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſſembling Age, that Faith ſo often breaks,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Learn hence to do more than the Proudeſt ſpeaks.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Speak not the Author's Praiſe; his Art commands,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Tongues ſhould be more crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led than our Hands;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:50921:54"/>
               <l> 
                  <hi>Nor can we ſcape (this Spight his ſpeed affords)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From being over-taken in our Words.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What ſhall become of their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which ſcatter'd through two hours Tautology.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gathered by theſe Characters, muſt hence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Endure the doom of ſuch as can ſpeak ſenſe?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But that thine Art's a Friend to Repetition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their hourly Breath; they'd damn the next Edition.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Print then that Praiſe which Volumes cannot hold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But in thine own compendious Figures told:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Figures, which make us duller-handed think</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Words from the Speaker's Mouth diſſolve to Ink;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:50921:54"/>
               <l> 
                  <hi>And fall upon thy Papers, or thy Quill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Made of ſome nimble Tongue gave thee this Skill.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still may that full-fledg'd Pen with moiſture ſpring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Snatch'd from the Eagles, not the Gooſes Wing.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>But that which would have been moſt uſeful to the Church of God, if it had pleaſed the Almighty to have granted him Life to finiſh it, was a Treatiſe call'd by him, <hi>Verba Chriſti,</hi> or, <hi>The Words of Chriſt.</hi> His deſign in it was this;</p>
            <p>He conſidered, how great an Eye-ſore it was to all good Men, to ſee Chriſtians perſecute each other, and as violently as thoſe of the ſame Religion had been Perſecuted in former Ages by the groſſeſt Hereticks, by
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50921:55"/> Jews or Heathen Infidels. His deſire therefore was to make enquiry (I now uſe his own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions) into the Cauſes and Reaſons why Chriſtians ſhould be ſo animated againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and having fix'd it in his Mind and Judgment, that all reaſons of this, and indeed of the decay of Chriſtianity in general, were to be reſolved into this one; namely, the not duly attending unto the Words of our Saviour; not only his Precepts and Doctrins, but all his Sayings.</p>
            <p>He therefore thought it not an unprofitable Task, to bring into one Body and Complex all the Words and Sayings of our Saviour, which lye diſperſed in the four Evangeliſts; making them appear in a diſtinct and larger Character from the Words
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:50921:55"/> with which they have a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary connexion and dependance. <hi>In the Words</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>uttered by our Saviours own Mouth, or by direct conſequences from them, we may find a Body of Divinity, a Complex of all neceſſary Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Truths, fundamental to the Faith. Here</hi> (added he) <hi>may be found ground for deciſion of Controverſies, ſo as to keep us from Erring damnably, or Sinning mortally; for reſolving all Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical Points of moment to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Here we might learn to direct and moderate our Paſſions, to attain and exerciſe all Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and ſhun all Vices. Here</hi> (ſaith our Prelate) <hi>patience to bear, and ſtrength to conquer all Afflictions. From our Saviours Lips have flowed words of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Conſolation to erect the Soul, when oppreſſed under heavieſt burthens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:50921:56"/>
            <p> So far as to the Reaſon and Foundation of his Work, now hear him as to the manner and platform of it. And that was this; he would endeavour to ſhew from the time in which, and the occaſion upon which, each ſaying was uttered by Our Saviour, the ſcope and drift of his Words, and what applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be made of them for our inſtruction; either to guide us in our Faith, or to direct us in our life, in ſeveral Caſes and Occurrences.</p>
            <p>This was the deſign, and this the method of the pious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in that imperfect Treatiſe of his, <hi>Verba Chriſti.</hi> A work truly worthy of its Author, and agreeable to the pacific temper of him in particular, and to the deſign of Chriſtianity in general. But his being ſnatch'd
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:50921:56"/> away by the rude hand of Death, in the very beginning of that undertaking, as the Learned and Pious Archbiſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> was in the proſecution of his Sacred Chronology, hath left it an Abortive. A loſs which as it cannot now be retrieved, is not enough to be lamented; ſince it might have contributed in part to allay the flames, and cool the heats among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; which adminiſter ſo much occaſion thereby of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to the common Enemies of our Faith, Jews, Mahometans and Heathens.</p>
            <p>And thô his Name ſhould not live in theſe his ſcattered Works, ſome of which notwithſtanding may eſcape the Teeth of Time, if not thoſe of Calumny; yet will he live, at leaſt, in the remembrance of all vertuous
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50921:57"/> and honeſt Men, who knew his real Merit and Worth. The Hopes which I have conceived of the duration of his unſpotted Fame, obliges me to haſten to a Concluſion, after I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to draw his Picture in Miniature, in Little; thô therein I ſtand in need of the Pencil of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin,</hi> or an <hi>Angelo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Learning (to begin with that which is not the leaſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſtic of a good Divine) was ſufficiently atteſted in thoſe public Exerciſes performed by him with ſo much Applauſe, and attended with ſo much Pomp (as hath been already mentioned) before that famous Univerſity, and which certainly wanted not many Men as fit to judge of worth, as there are others to cenſure it without any Title to that unmannerly
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50921:57"/> Freedom, but Confidence and Ignorance.</p>
            <p>How his Preaching was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd and valued in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, hath been already ſhewn; and with ſo clear a demonſtration, that Venerable Antiquity cannot furniſh us with many parallel Inſtances. 'Tis true, in his Elder years he had declined to uſe that florid way of Preaching, for which he had been ſo much celebrated in his Younger times; and thô after that he affected no pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Expreſſions, no gawdy Oratory; yet were his Reaſons maſculine, his Arguments co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and his Phraſe plain and clear; and have offence to none but ſome ſuperficial Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: Perſons who applaud nothing but their own Tinſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and conſequently judged
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:50921:58"/> his ſtudied Plainneſs to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with the deſign of a Pulpit-harangue.</p>
            <p>His Humility ſet off all his other Vertues, like a Diamond in a Ring; and was ſo conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, that, thô it gave a greater luſtre thereto among good and ſober Men; yet did his humble condeſcenſion to the meaneſt of Men, and eſpecially to any of thoſe who had a Ray of the Immortal Wiſdom dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their Souls, ſeem to leſſen him among the unthink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rabble, who being ſtrangers to his real Worth, reſolved to diminiſh it.</p>
            <p>And thô he was remarkable for this laſt Vertue, and which may be ſaid (at leaſt) to be the Nurſe of the reſt; yet as he in all Buſineſſes of moment pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered long with himſelf all the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:50921:58"/> Cauſes and Circumſtances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and reſolved them into Caſes of Conſcience, when he had once thus ſatisfied his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conſulted therein his Judgment, 'twas not the inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of the promiſing Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer that could perſwade, nor the frowns of the Great that could byaſs or withdraw him from his Poſt, and from the lines of Juſt and Right; althô in more minute Matters he might in ſome Caſes be impoſed upon, by his Credulity to thoſe who therein pretended to adviſe him. And, to finiſh that part of his Portraiture, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Public Concerns he ſhew'd himſelf to be both Prudent and Couragious. In all Affronts or Reproaches caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as a Private Man, his Reaſon and ſweet Temper ſo
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50921:59"/> far ſubdu'd his paſſionate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments, as not to ſtudy any Revenge againſt the Offender. He would have look'd upon himſelf as a notorious Violater of the Divine Precepts, if he did not forgive Injuries, and write them in the Duſt. The tart Reflections which enſued ſuch a Crime, as the meditating a Revenge, were made upon himſelf; and he inferr'd, That God was diſpleaſed with his ways, ſince thoſe became his Enemies whom he had obliged to a more Friendly procedure, by his having formerly loaden them with Kindneſſes. For he uſed to ſay; It was juſt with God to ſuffer him to be ſo ill uſed by Men, who had been far more ingrateful to God. And, if herein ſome ſallies of Paſſion ſhewed, that he was a Man;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:50921:59"/> his quick correction of them ſhewed, that he was a Chriſtian. How patiently, and how calmly did he often reſent ſuch Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to his private Perſon! of which all the above-mentioned Diſcourſe is intended.</p>
            <p>His Piety might be read in viſible Characters, in his public Actions, and was beſt drawn by his own Pencil in his Diaries, and in keeping his Birth-day with Faſting and Prayers; ſome of which I have here added, that by this taſte the Reader may perceive, how near this Prelates Devotion came to the warm Zeal and vigorous Piety of the Chriſtians of the firſt Ages; and how much his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble complaining of his Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the mean performances of his Duty, when at beſt, ſuits with their holy Practices.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:50921:60"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Meditations on</hi> April 20. 1681. <hi>by Dr.</hi> Edward Rainbow.</p>
            <q>
               <p>WHen I make a ſerious retroſpect into the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Stages of my paſt Life, I cannot but acknowledge a continued Series of merciful Providences from God towards me in my ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Capacities; but I have cauſe to lament, that my Returns have been very unſuitable.</p>
               <p>God aſſiſt me with his Holy Spirit, and Wiſdom, and grant, that I may improve my left Talent, and all the remaining Moments of my Life, to gain a comfortable aſſurance, That Death ſhall open a Gate to let my Soul paſs out of the old Priſon of this Body,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:50921:60"/> into that Freedom to which the Son of God gives right, even to the glorious liberty of the Sons of God. O, that I might ſo preach him in his Kingdom of Grace, that I may be one, thô the meaneſt in his Kingdom of Glory!</p>
            </q>
            <p>Meditations on <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1652. after a Recovery from a Cold with a Cough.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOrd! thy Mercy is moſt ſeen in Judgment, when it is not lengthened to Eternity. If I had not now felt the ſmart of this one Twig of thy Rod, I had ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly perſevered in an incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſobedience. But by this Touch thou haſt graciouſly healed me of that, giving me time and</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:50921:61"/> 
                  <hi>opportunity to look up at thee, now admoniſhing by thy Finger. From this I ſee nothing but the ſweetneſs, indulgence and mercy of a wiſe Father: In my ſelf no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſtubbornneſs and rebellion of a perverſe Child. O, how have I abuſed a longer reign of Health for now well nigh Thirty years!</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>If I ſhould write all his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, I might tranſcribe a good part of his Diary.</p>
            <p>You have here had a Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of his private Devotion; in the next and laſt place we ſhall conſider, whether his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality to the Poor and Needy was agreeable to his Sacred Character, or no.</p>
            <p>In examining his Actions by the Teſt of this Vertue, we ſhall find that he left a large
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:50921:61"/> Inventory of charitable Deeds. And, as <hi>Nerva Coeſar</hi> was called <hi>Pater Patrioe,</hi> the Father of his Country, by reaſon of his gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and kind Government; ſo might he be termed <hi>Pater Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum,</hi> the Father of the Poor, for his liberal Donative to them, unto whom his Compaſſion was never deny'd, nor his Hand cloſed up, without ſomething to warm their Hearts and chear their Spirits; and what was ſtill more obliging, what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed was with a free heart, taking pleaſure in the good Offices he did any of thoſe Myſtical Members of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To deſcend to particularize the ſeveral methods of this Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Charity, after he came to be ſo, would look ſomething like Flattery; ſuch variety did
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:50921:62"/> he uſe in the diſpenſing the Goods of Fortune to his Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Brethren; ſince the Proverb in theſe Dregs of Time proves too true, which aſſerts the great diſuſe of that moſt extorting Uſury, when the Uſe out-ſtrips the Principal.</p>
            <p>To proceed; He uſually gave 20 <hi>s.</hi> to the Poor at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> when it was his turn to Preach there, that his Liberality might tempt them to liſten to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin. His Allowance to the Poor of <hi>Dalſton</hi> Pariſh (within the Limits of which <hi>Roſe Caſtle</hi> ſtands) was 30 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what was given them at his Caſtle-Gates, and to Sick People; not to mention, what was given them at Sacraments, and upon other occaſions. In Dear Years, when his own ſtock of Corn was ſpent, he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:50921:62"/> ordered Barley to be bought at 12 <hi>s.</hi> or 14 <hi>s. per</hi> Buſhel, and to be given to the Poor; which came then in ſuch great numbers to the Gates, that the Porter who ſerved them, having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the curioſity to tell them, affirmed, that he often ſerv'd Seven or Eightſcore People in one and the ſame day. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Mony to a School Maſter for teaching Eight Poor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Read, at <hi>Dalſton.</hi> He put out Poor Boys to Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices. In Penſions to Poor Scholars at the Univerſity, and to ſome Indigent Perſons he gave 32 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> conſtantly, for ſeveral Years. To which may be added, his ſhare with other Biſhops in yearly Penſions to Forein Converts, and to other publick Charities, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church;
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:50921:63"/> to <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants large Sums, &amp;c. Nay, his Charity was often ſo extenſive, that he forgat his own Secular Intereſt to lend unto God, by his Largeſſes to the Needy.</p>
            <p>At his Death, he gave to the Poor of eight or nine Pariſhes, and in ſome other Modes of Charity, which amounted to the Sum of 200 <hi>l.</hi> And what that pious Prelate left, his Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow punctually performed. For as ſhe loved him entirely; ſo did ſhe ſhew her true reſpect for his Memory, in enlarging his gift. And thus that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Couple, as they ſtrove whether ſhould love more; ſo did they rival each other in Charity.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:50921:63"/>
            <p> Moreover I ſhould be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious the memory of this good Biſhop, if I ſhould not further add, that beſides theſe Public Acts of Liberality, his Charity was yet in ſome reſpects ſo ſecret (according to our Bleſſed Saviour's Advice) that he kept a Private Purſe for that end, and that ſo private, that even his dear Conſort, the Partner of all his Joys and other Counſels, was a Stranger to it; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how he diſpoſed of it, till he himſelf diſcovered to her a little before his death where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about 20 <hi>l.</hi> of that Mony lay, which he deſired might be given to three or four of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, or to ſome decayed Gentleman of honeſt Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; and that without naming of him. Which his Loving Conſort accordingly performed.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:50921:64"/> This laſt Act is not only a plain demonſtration of his extenſive Bounty, but how far he was from that pompous and oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Charity, which is made (by too many) the foundation of Merit in another Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>And, as his Kindneſs was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited to the corporal Wants of the Needy; ſo no leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate was he to thoſe who went aſtray from the true Fold. To ſuch he uſed lenity and mildneſs, endeavouring to bring them into the way by ſtrong Argumenrs and ſoft Words; convincing their erronious Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by Reaſon and Scripture, rather than by affrighting them with Corporal puniſhments out of that by-way into which they had fallen by miſtake. As to his own Practice, none could be
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:50921:64"/> more obſervant of the Rules of the Church of <hi>England</hi> than he was; thô he pitied the Errors of others, who differed from him in Opinion.</p>
            <p>To conclude, May this mean Monument, which I have ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Memory of this Right Reverend Prelate, ſuffice to continue his Name, and the Hiſtory of his Vertues to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages, and that thereby the luſtre of his Pious Actions may ſo ſhine forth in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched and profligate Age, that others may be induced to Copy after ſo fair an Example; ſerving God faithfully and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely in this Life, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him eternally in that which is to come.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:50921:65"/>
               <bibl>Epheſ. 3. 20</bibl>Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the power that worketh in us; unto him be glory in the Church, by Chriſt Jeſus, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Ages, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50921:65"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the Funeral of the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Edward,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>REV. XIV. 13.</bibl>
               <q>And I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me write, Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord from henceforth; yea, ſaith the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen <hi>Moſes</hi> died, God himſelf Interr'd him with the expence of a Miracle, <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 34. 6.</note> and beſtowed the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Title of Honour upon him in this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50921:66"/> Epitaph, <hi>Moſes my Servant is dead.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 1. 2.</note> And here we have <hi>a Voice from Heaven</hi> directing <hi>John</hi> the Divine to write a Text, proper for the Funeral of a Prophet in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſuch an one as gives us the ſad Occaſion of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the laſt Office of our Duty and Charity at this Mournful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. Sad it is to us, <hi>For knoweſt thou not that the Lord hath taken away</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>thy Maſter from thy head to day?</hi> as the Sons of the Prophets ſaid of <hi>Elijah.</hi> But to him who lived to Chriſt, to dye is gain, <hi>and the day of his death better than the day of his birth.</hi> The one brought him into a Vale of Miſery, where his days were to be <hi>few, and full of trouble;</hi> the other we hope has advanc'd him to a Region far above aſſaults of Mutability, where his Happineſs ſhall be as Eternal, as God the Author and the Object of it. Where they <hi>who dye in the Lord,</hi> ſhall ſing an everlaſting <hi>Requiem</hi> to their Souls; nothing of the buſle of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50921:66"/> this life attend them, but their <hi>Works;</hi> and they from thenceforth, as ſaith the Spirit, <hi>reſt from their labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Criticks read the words thus; <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that are in the Lord, which die within a while,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And then by the Connexion this Verſe ſeems to have with the former. which ſpeaks of the patience of the Saints, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we render <hi>Labours,</hi> they underſtand <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> and ſo take the Text to be a particular Prediction of the bloody and ſevere Tyranny under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> when they were happy, moſt happy who were <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered unto their graves in peace, where the wicked ceaſe from troubling,</hi> that <hi>their eyes ſhould ſee all the evil</hi> which was coming upon the Church of God. Now thô perhaps this may be the Strict and Primary meaning of the Heavenly <hi>Voice,</hi> yet the words are but too applicable to our preſent Times, even in this ſence: for thô we are not now under the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50921:67"/> of Heathen Emperours, but have Kings for our Nurſing Fathers; yet 'tis Scripture ſtill; <hi>All that will live</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</hi> Satan has his Agents even in the outward viſible Church. <hi>Have not I choſen you twelve, and one of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 6. 70.</note> 
               <hi>you is a Devil?</hi> and theſe have ſo much of the Helliſh temper and Complexion of their Father, that they rejoyce and triumph in running down all the practices of an Holy life, which in the Judgment of the Holy Ghoſt (if perhaps they have heard whether there be any Holy Ghoſt, or no) is looked upon as Perſecution; as plainly appears by comparing <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 9. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29. in the caſe between <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac.</hi> I hope ſome mens Conſciences will tell them, what Unchriſtian oppoſition this moſt Pious and Right Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late has been forced to conteſt with, purely for his ſteady reſolution of Religiouſly executing the weighty Charge of his Sacred Function, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50921:67"/> ſo ſave me the ungrateful task of doing it.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall take the Words in the moſt obvious and eaſie ſence, as they in general import the Bleſſed eſtate of thoſe who dye in the Lord. And to handle this in the beſt method I am able to reduce my haſty and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Meditations to, 'twill be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that I (firſt) explain what it is to die in the Lord. After which I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, wherein the bleſſedneſs of that Eſtate conſiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which I ſhall illuſtrate,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by repreſenting unto you the Emptineſs and Diſſatisfaction of all Worldly Enjoyments from which they are delivered; ſuggeſted in theſe words, <hi>for they reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by ſhewing that poſitive and ſuperabundant Satifaction, that glorious recompence of Reward, which they ſhall meet with in a better World; couched in theſe words, <hi>and their works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50921:68"/>
            <p> Firſt then, What it is to die in the Lord.</p>
            <p>To die in the Lord, is to die in the true Chriſtian Faith. But then by Faith, we muſt not mean the bare profeſſion of an Hiſtorical belief; but the Cordial and Sincere Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the Promiſes of the Goſpel upon the Conditions they are offered to us. This is ſo comprehenſive a Subject, that it implies the whole Duty of Man; and cannot be fully deſcribed, unleſs I ſhould either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with the Original (the New Teſtament) or with the lively tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of it, in the Hiſtory of our departed Fathers life; in which the Severeſt Eye might gratiſie its Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in viewing thoſe refined ſtroaks which the Pencil of God had drawn upon his Soul; in beholding with Veneration the awful and Majeſtic Character of his Maker Signally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon all the Powers and Faculties of his Mind: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 'Twas indeed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50921:68"/> an Inſtructive ſight to thoſe who had the honour and happineſs of his more immediate Converſe, to ſee the many Originals of Chriſtianity, which lay ſcattered and diſperſed in the Writings of the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, elegantly contracted in the Syſtem of his Actions, unto a perfect Man of God, <hi>unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> How exemplary was his Meekneſs in bearing the rudeneſs, the Inſolence and Indignities of ſome, whom the common Obligation of Religion, as well as the more ſpecial Tyes of their peculiar Subjection, might have taught more duty and obſervance? How familiar was his Converſe, and of how eaſie Acceſs was he to the meaneſt Chriſtian, treating them more like Brethren, than Sons in Chriſt? Having always before his eyes both the Command and Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of his Saviour, <hi>He that is greateſt among you ſhall be your Servant.</hi> With <note place="margin">Math. 23. 11.</note> how tender and compaſſionate a ſence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50921:69"/> did his Bowels earn upon the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of his poor Brethren; whom he freely relieved with the moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged Heart and open hand! O how often have the <hi>Loins</hi> of the naked <hi>bleſſed him, for being warmed with the fleece of his Sheep!</hi> His <note place="margin">Job 31. 20.</note> Liberality and Charity were as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive as the obligation of his duty. His Riches conſiſted moſt in good Works; he was indeed a faithful Steward, who carefully employed the Talent God intruſted him with, to the uſe and ſervice of Chriſts Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers upon Earth: for the only Uſury he ever put his Mony too, was in thus <hi>lending to the Lord;</hi> which he did, not out of any Phariſaical affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Popularity or Applauſe; to avoid that, he ſo induſtriouſly ſtudied a modeſt Secrecy, <hi>that his left hand knew not what his right hand did.</hi> By which means he loſt indeed what he never valued, the Fame and Reputation of it, being ſeen of men; looking up rather unto him,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50921:69"/> who then ſaw him in ſecret, and will one day reward him openly.</p>
            <p>How admirable was his Humility, both in his Civil and Spiritual Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city! which his earneſt deſire of being Interr'd among the meaneſt of thoſe that own the ſame common Saviour and Redeemer, will teſtifie to all Poſterity. As for the Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry of Funeral Pomp, and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial voice of Monuments; he looked not upon them as Enſigns of Honour, but rather as Trophies erected by Death, in memory of that fatal Victory Sin got over us in the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> when we became like the Beaſts that periſh. But thô his Merit and Vertue do loudly call for all the Juſtice Oratory can do them, yet I dread to diſturb his Sacred reſt, by prophaning the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of his laſt, peremptory, dying Command, that I ſhould, (to expreſs my ſelf in his own words) be very ſparing in any Character of him: But yet the Modeſty of the dead
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50921:70"/> muſt not rob the living, of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and happy Influence the manner of his death may have upon every one that hears it. My Text leads me directly to that: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his was ſuch a Raviſhment to all that beheld it, that their Hearts grew warm within them, ready to break out into that pathetic Expreſſion of the Apoſtle. <hi>Let us alſo go, that we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 16.</note> 
               <hi>may die with him.</hi> And whenever thou, O God the Lord, to whom belong the Iſſues of Life and Death, ſhalt call us to follow him; <hi>O let us die the death of this righteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 23. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and let our laſt end be like his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twas admirable to obſerve with what ſubmiſſive Humility and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Devotion he received his laſt Sickneſs as the Meſſenger of Death: How ſteadily he maintained a Divine temper of Mind, without the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent and vain interruption of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Concerns; vigorous Ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fervent Prayers, holy Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeaſonable, prudent and pious
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50921:70"/> Advice, were the conſtant Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his heavenly Soul; till his weak and languiſhing Voice conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Period of his life with this pious and ſubmiſſive Expreſſion; <hi>God has now taken from me the uſe of my Tongue but I deſire you all to employ yours in Prayers to him for me.</hi> This ſweet diſpoſition of Spirit was ſo pleaſing to God, that he therefore ſeemed to diſſolve his earthly Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle without either pain or ſickneſs, on purpoſe that the Troubles of a Body might not interrupt the Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Serenity of his Soul.</p>
            <p>Thus he lived, Copying out through the whole tenor and ſeries of his Actions, the Noble draught St. <hi>Paul</hi> has left of a good Biſhop (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.) adorning his Sacred Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the glorious variety of all thoſe Graces which qualifie the Man of God to bear the Character of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador from Heaven. And thus <hi>he died in the Lord.</hi> Is not he then bleſſed? <hi>Yea, ſaith the Spirit.</hi> And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50921:71"/> this leads me in the ſecond place, to ſhew wherein the bleſſedneſs of that Eſtate conſiſts. And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In being delivered from the toyl and fatigue, the emptineſs and diſſatisfaction of things below. To read the many Noble Diſcourſes the Heathen Philoſophers have tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Poſterity of the emptineſs and inſignificancy of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enjoyments of Life, thoſe Toys and Bables upon which we fool away the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the precious time God has put into our hands to ſecure unto our Selves a bleſſed Eternity, were ſufficient to give any thinking man an Eternal diſguſt againſt them. So little happineſs could thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Wits, and great Maſters of Reaſon, find in the fluttering Pomp of temporal Grandure. But if you are not ſatisfied with the Authority of the Heathen (thô herein they uttered the genuine Oracles of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;) why, then let us refer the Determination of the Point to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:50921:71"/> a perſon peculiarly qualified to be Judge in the Caſe, both in reſpect of the Excellent Spirit of Wiſdom that was in him and becauſe he is one that ſtuck not to gratifie his Curioſity in trying all Experiments of that Nature; <hi>for he gave his heart</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>to know madneſs and folly,</hi> as <hi>well as wiſdom.</hi> And what was the reſult of all? Why, after this glorious and potent Monarch had made <hi>Silver in Jeruſalem as Stones for abundance,</hi> and <note place="margin">1 King. 10. 27. 1 King. 11. 3.</note> had taken him a <hi>thouſand Wives and Concubines,</hi> erected him Magnificent Buildings, planted him delicious Vineyards, fruitful Orchards, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Gardens, adorn'd with Lillies, more ſplendidly arrayed than he himſelf in all his glory; after he had gotten him great Poſſeſſions, Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous choice of Men Singers and Women Singers, and the delights of the Sons of Men, and denied himſelf nothing that his Eyes deſired, nor withheld his heart from any Joy; and having thus contracted unto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50921:72"/> himſelf an Epitomy of the Worlds glory, he might well ask, <hi>What can the man do that cometh after the King?</hi> yet this King confeſſeth, that <hi>when he had looked on all the works that his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 2. from ver. 1. to ver. 13.</note> 
               <hi>hands had wrought, and on the labour that he had laboured to do, behold all was vanity and vexation of Spirit, and there was no profit under the Sun.</hi> Believe it, if <hi>Solomon,</hi> whom both Nature and Art ſo highly conſpired to divert and pleaſe, yet Nauſeated all as <hi>Vanity;</hi> 'twere but common Prudence in us to ſet our Hearts at reſt, who have neither the thouſandth part of <hi>Solomons</hi> Grandeur, nor of his Wit neither, to improve the ſmall ſtock we have to the beſt advantage. Yet, ſay we had all the Kingdoms of the World, and the glory of them, as they were moſt artificially drawn to the life in a tempting Landskip, preſented by Satan to our Saviours Imagination, yet ſince <hi>all that is in the World is but either the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, or the pride</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50921:72"/> 
               <hi>of life; i. e.</hi> Pleaſure, Riches, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as we are told by S. <hi>John,</hi> who liv'd long enough in the World to know what it afforded. 'Tis the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Grand Fundamental Error, and folly of our whole lives, to look for any happineſs in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them. Human Beatitude conſiſts in the gratification of thoſe Faculties which make Man, <hi>i. e.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect and Will; the perfective qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of which are Truth in the Underſtanding, and Rectitude or Holineſs in the Will. Now could any of the fore-mentioned Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments make a man either more Wiſe or more Vertuous than his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; Could they ſecure us from being impos'd upon by falſe Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Ignorance and Error, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the darkneſs of our Minds with clear Conceptions of Truth, that Secret of the Moſt High GOD; with certain knowledge of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Works of Nature, and GOD the Myſterious Author of them;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50921:73"/> or with Prudence in the rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our Actions, which would be the Glory and Ornament of our Underſtanding; Could they redeem us from the ſhameful Captivity of ſordid Appetites, and Vile Affections, which like Rebel Vaſſals dethrone the Sovereign Goodneſs that ſhould Reign within us; Could they reſtore again that generous Magnanimity, Temperance, Juſtice, and Univerſal Complacency in what is good and honourable to its Empire in the Soul, which would be the grace and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Will; Could they but ſecure unto us the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> the bleſſed Hopes of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Felicity in the next World, when we leave them behind us, and bid them Adieu for ever, which is the only Foundation whereupon we may build a firm peace and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted comfort; I grant they were richly worth all the Care, Anxiety and Toil, we expend in the proſecution of them. But alas! they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50921:73"/> are meer Emptineſs, and nothing; ſo phantaſtical and airy, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude our Embraces, when we think to enjoy them moſt. As for Riches, <hi>the Eye is not ſatisfied with them,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4. 8.</note> 
               <hi>thô we labour and bereave our Souls of good;</hi> firſt to procure, and then to keep them; and after the Poor Wretch hath ſpent himſelf in drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, <hi>he ſhall leave them in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 17. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the midſt of his days, and at his end ſhall be a Fool.</hi> And pray what is Honour, that Idol of Worldly men? <hi>We know that an Idol is nothing in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the World,</hi> ſo is Honour too; too thin and too airy to yield any ſolid, real ſatisfaction: It puffs a man up indeed, and blows him a little bigger than his Neighbour; but the Timpany renders him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie both to himſelf and others; and when God ſends him <hi>a Thorn in the Fleſh,</hi> it pricks the Bladder, and the gawdy Bubble vaniſheth. <hi>This is Pharaoh and all his multitude.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 31. 18.</note> And as for Pleaſures (ſuch I mean
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50921:74"/> as the Voluptuary calls ſo;) why, grant the Epicure (which yet he rarely meets with) a lucky concurrence of all that can poſſibly advance a delight, the Spirits are preſently exalted into a Rapture, and ſo the goodly Tranſport dies in a moment, leaving Penitential Nature to repair the damage and Prodigal expence of a ſhort Extravagance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What profit then hath he that hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>laboured for the Wind?</hi> So little Satisfaction can the Creatures afford, which themſelves <hi>groan and travel in pain</hi> under the bondage of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the primitive Curſe of Sin. Indeed had Man been created like the Angels in Heaven, all Soul and Spirit, and not tyed to the cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom luggage of a Body; he had then been free from all the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Calamities which attend a Mortal State. But ſince we are doom'd to dwell <hi>in theſe Houſes of Clay, whoſe foundation is in the duſt; Every man in his beſt Eſtate is</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50921:74"/> 
               <hi>altogether Vanity;</hi> And yet, while we do Sojourn in theſe tottering Tabernacles, the Natural Reſpect we bear to the Noble Gueſt that lodges in them, puts us to a vaſt expence and trouble in Repairing the Decays, and patching up the Ruines of them. This indeed is but good Husbandry. But when I obſerve the prodigal and luxurious Ornament ſome beſtow upon this mean Cottage, I can hardly hold from asking them <hi>Socrates</hi> his Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>What do you mean, to make your Priſon ſo ſtrong?</hi> And yet when they have done all, the Tenure of them is but for life under an Arbitrary Lord; and how ſoon that Leaſe may expire we none of us know; perhaps <hi>this Night may our Souls be required of us.</hi> However, at the furtheſt, <hi>the Age of Man is threeſcore years and ten; or if he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 10.</note> 
               <hi>come to fourſcore years, yet is his ſtrength then but labour and ſorrow, ſo ſoon paſſeth it away and we are gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50921:75"/>
            <p> Thus much concerning the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of their Eſtate who dye in the Lord, in their being delivered from the Toyl and Fatigue, the Emptineſs and Diſſatisfaction of things below.</p>
            <p>The ſecond and laſt Topic I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſhew it from, was that poſitive and ſuperabundant ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, that glorious recompence of Reward, which they ſhall meet with in another World; couched in theſe words, and <hi>their works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Man apoſtatized from the Allegiance he owed his Maker; he fell under the Power and Dominion of Sin, and Sin delivered over the Captive Rebel to the Bondage and Tyranny of Death, which gnawed revengfully upon his Fleſh in the Grave, and tortured his polluted Soul, upon the Eternal Rack of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and Deſpair in Hell: Hell,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50921:75"/> originally prepared for the Arch-Rebel of Heaven, the great <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> of Sin, and his Accurſed Train; but now become the common Gaol of Men and Devils; <hi>Such a Prince of Terrors</hi> is Death, when arm'd with the poyſonous <hi>Sting of Sin.</hi> But the <hi>Captain of our Salvation</hi> has conquered Death, and diſarm'd it of that power it had got over us by Sin. See how the Apoſtle tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs over it in the Leſſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for this Solemnity: <hi>O Death</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 55, 56.</note> 
               <hi>where is thy Sting? O Grave, where is thy Victory? The Sting of Death is Sin, and the ſtrength of Sin is the Law; i. e.</hi> There is nothing makes Death like a Serpent, able to hurt us, but Sin; without which the Grave is but a Bed, wherein we take a long Lethargic Sleep: And that which impowers Sin to do us miſchief, is the Law, which prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits it, and conſequently involves us in the Curſe, due to our Guilt. <hi>But thanks be to God who giveth us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50921:76"/> 
               <hi>the Victory thrô our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Bleſſed be the Father of Mercies, who (by what Chriſt hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one for us) hath gotten us the Victory over Sin, and by this happy Conqueſt, has made Death only a Silent paſſage to a glorious Immortality; where they who <hi>dye in the Lord</hi> ſhall for ever (for ever) enjoy ſuch Divine Tranſports of Soul, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>which it is not lawful for a man to utter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 4.</note> ſaid the Eloquent S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when the over flowing ſenſe of them rapt him into Extaſie. Bleſſed Souls! which always behold the Face of God, <hi>in whoſe preſence, is fulneſs of Joy for evermore.</hi> A ſight, even a bare ſight, able to transform us into his own likeneſs, and make our Faces <hi>(like the face of Moſes)</hi> too bright and dazling for any mortal Eye to look upon. <hi>We ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note> Bleſſed are thoſe that-ſtand before the Lamb of God in his Throne of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50921:76"/> Glory; that are admitted into the Society of the Cherubims and Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims, thoſe ſprightly Choiriſters of Heaven, where nothing is heard, but the voice of Joy and Gladneſs. There's no Sin to ſtain their white Robes of Purity, or eclipſe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Emanations of Light which they receive from the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; no Jealouſies or Fears to diſturb their Enjoyments; neither can any imperfection taint that ſtate, where <hi>God ſhall be all in all.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Surely now the <hi>Bleſſedneſs of dying in the Lord</hi> is ſo raviſhing a Contemplation, as even to make S. <hi>Johns</hi> Wiſh the language of all our Souls; <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 20</note> 
               <hi>quiokly.</hi> And indeed the happineſs of our future Life is not fully and ſenſibly revealed unto us, but ſeems on purpoſe to <hi>be hid with Chriſt in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> that we might not be too reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and impatient under the burden of Mortality; nor break the Priſon of our Bodies, to redeem our Souls
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50921:77"/> into <hi>the glorious liberty of the Sons of God. Dii coelant homines, ut vivere durent, quam ſit dulce Mori.</hi> So then the ſame bleſſed Providence of God, which in mercy to his Church continued our Departed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo long among us, has now in mercy to himſelf, tranſlated him to the Church Triumphant, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed his Mitre for a Crown, <hi>for a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> And <hi>he who turn'd many to Righteouſneſs, now ſhines as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of my Text; and ſhall only beg your patience for a ſhort Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Inference or two, and then you ſhall ſee this Right Reverend Prelate pay his laſt Debt to the Law; <hi>Duſt thou art, and unto Duſt thou ſhalt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>return.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50921:77"/>
            <p> The firſt Inference ſhall be for ſuch as are more particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Loſs of a great and worthy Friend, a dear and kind Relation; which I draw from the Conſideration of the bleſſed Eſtate of thoſe that are departed in the Lord: And 'tis this in the Apoſtles words, <hi>that ye ſorrow not as others,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>which have no hope.</hi> Were we Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and looked upon Death as the Annihilation of our Souls; or Sadducees, <hi>who deny that there is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 20. 27.</note> 
               <hi>any Reſurrection;</hi> or Papiſts, who dream of a frightful place called <hi>Purgatory,</hi> we might then juſtly either bewail the utter periſhing of the Dead, or the Miſery of their State. But ſince we believe the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they <hi>are bleſſed in reſting from their labours, and that their works follow them;</hi> what reaſon have we to lament the End of that Life, which is the Period of our Miſery, and the beginning of a happy Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? Ay, but ſaid the Jews, when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50921:78"/> our Saviour wept over the Sepulchre of his <hi>Friend</hi> Lazarus, <hi>See how he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 36.</note> 
               <hi>loved him.</hi> Alas! they miſtook the cauſe of our Saviours Tears; which flowed only from his Compaſſion to poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who was now again to lanch into the deep, after he had weathered the Harbour where his Soul was at Reſt. 'Tis like indeed we would have been glad to have enjoyed him longer, he was ſo kind a Friend: but is it not prepoſterous to commemorate the kindneſs of a Friend with ſo high an Argument of Ill nature, as to repine at his being happy ſooner, than we expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? God was more merciful to him than it ſeems we ſhould have been, that would have kept him longer out of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Boſom,</hi> only that we might have hugged him in our own. Could he but look down as low as us, he would certainly ſay, <hi>Daughters of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves; I am comforted,</hi> having
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50921:78"/> received the Wages of my Labours in the Evening of my days; <hi>but you are tormented,</hi> that have the <hi>heat and burden of the day</hi> to bear. Wherefore <hi>comfort one another with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4. 18.</note> 
               <hi>theſe words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Inference is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concern of all that hear me, taken from the Conſideration of the toil and labour of this World, <hi>viz.</hi> to wean us from too paſſionate love of it.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſo Childiſh an Infirmity to doat upon Shadows, and catch at them, that methinks we ſhould bluſh when we are <hi>become men, not to have put away ſuch Childiſh things,</hi> but ſtill to walk on in <hi>a vain ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and diſquiet our ſelves in vain.</hi> But thô we have all of us ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently experienced the Cheats and diſappointments of a falſe uneaſie World; yet the Magnetiſm of the Earth does ſo powerfully attract our Affections, that thô <hi>we live</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50921:79"/> 
               <hi>long and ſee not the Grave,</hi> yet we are apt to complain with <hi>Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> of the ſhortneſs of our days, and are ſtill crying, <hi>O ſpare me a little!</hi> as if we were in love with impotence and pains, and loath to retire to the only place <hi>where the weary be at reſt.</hi> But if all Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from the Vanity of what we purſue, be ineffectual to convince us of the folly of it; yet certainly 'tis a Perfidiouſneſs below the Ingenuous Spirit of a Chriſtian, baſely to Eſpouſe his Soul to what he moſt ſolemnly renounced in his Baptiſm. That were equally our Sin in prevaricating with God, who will not be mocked; and our Miſery too, in meanly placing our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Sordid things below, that bear no proportion to the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of a Rational Agent, becauſe they are too capacious and ſublime, ever to be ſatisfied with any thing leſs than the full Diſplay of GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the glory of all his Attributes.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50921:79"/> 
               <hi>But this I ſay Brethren, the time is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 29.</note> 
               <hi>ſhort, it remaineth that both they that weep, be as thô they wept not; and they that buy, as thô they poſſeſſed not; and they that uſe this World, as not abuſing it; for the faſhion of this World paſſeth away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I pray God give us Grace, ſo to paſs thrô things Temporal, that we finally loſe not things Eternal; for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Reſurrection and the Life. <hi>To whom with the Father and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit of Grace, be aſcribed all Power, Glory, and Praiſe, for Ever and Ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
